December 1933
（すず）
うちはよう ぼーっとした子じゃ
言われとって
People always described me
as being so distracted.
Hey!
（船頭）おーい
Where are you heading to?
どこへ行くんだ？
I'm delivering seaweed to Futaba
in Nakajima Honmachi.
（すず）中島本町(なかじまほんまち)の
〝ふたば〞まで―
のりを届けるのです
本来は兄の役目でしたが
風邪のため―
This is usually my brother's
job, but he has a cold so...
私が代理を務…
I must fu... fulfill...
（船頭）
そら 感心じゃが
はあ やめえ やめえ
It's okay.
You don't have to be so formal.
砂利舟の戻りじゃけん
散らばっとろうが
Don't mind the gravel
on the floor.
After I'm done,
（すず）ほいで のりを届けたら
兄と妹にお土産を買(こ)うて帰るのです
I'm buying treats for
my brother and sister.
（船頭）ほうほう
I see.
Look. We're almost there.
（船頭）ほーれ
（すず）ウフフ…
（船頭）もう着くで
Hey, stop gazing off into space!
おう ぼーっとしとらんで おい
（すず）よいしょ
"Year's End Market"
（街のけん騒）
（すず）チョコレート 10銭
キャラメル大箱 10銭
Chocolate, 10 sen.
Box of caramels, 10 sen.
小箱 ５銭
ヨーヨーは10銭
Small box, 5 sen.
Yo-yo, 10 sen.
（子供）そうそう 上手 上手
（町人）うち 赤いのがええわ
I want the red one.
Business is still busy.
（町人）まだまだ賑わってますな
（町人）本当
（商人）
毎度 ありがとうございます
Thank you for coming. Take care.
足元 気をつけて
♪～
The sky's brilliance
Flows into my heart
Today again, I gaze far away
And tears trickle down
White clouds keep drifting past
While dreams entangle about
Wavering, fleeting
Sadness enveloping
It pains me to ponder
This emptiness evermore
Will salvation ever come?
In This Corner of the World
～♪
（すず）そこで道に迷うとったら
Then I got lost,
こんとな おいさんに出会(でお)うたん
and I met an old man.
（すみ）すずちゃん 何ね？ それ
Suzu,
what is that?
A monster.
（すず）“ばけもん”
（すみ）え？
At least that's what he said.
（すず）って言いんさった
これで道探せって
望遠鏡 のぞかせてくれんさった
He lent me his telescope
and told me to find my way.
Wow! I can see really well!
（すず）わあ！ よう見えるねえ
うわ！
落ちた籠ん中に
知らんにいさんが おりんさった
Then I fell into his basket
and met an older boy.
He's a kidnapper and
we're being kidnapped.
（周作(しゅうさく)）あいつは人さらい
わしらは さらわれた人たちじゃ
（すず）えっ!?
What? Oh, no...
弱ったねえ
I have to feed the chicken
before it gets dark.
夕方には 鶏の餌やりに
帰らんといけんのに
わしも父さんと
汽車で帰らんといけんのに
I have to ride the train
back home with my dad.
Me too, me too.
（ばけもん）わしも わしも
夜が来る前に帰らんと
えらいことになる
I have to go home
before night fall or else...
Or else what happens?
（すみ）
どう えらいことになるんじゃろ
（すず）まあ 見とりんさい
You'll see soon enough.
（すず）おっさん おっさん
（ばけもん）あいたっ あいたっ
- Hey mister.
- Oh! Ouch!
What is that? Take a look!
こりゃ 何じゃろうか？
のぞいてみて
うん？ どれどれ
Let me see.
（倒れる音）
（いびき）
He falls asleep when it gets dark.
（すず）夜になると寝てしまうと
いうことじゃったんじゃ
Too bad he'll miss supper.
（周作）こいつも
晩ご飯がのうなって気の毒じゃ
あんがとな 浦野(うらの)すず
Thanks, Suzu Urano!
（すず）
ありゃ いつの間に うちの名前を
How do you know my name?
（すみの笑い声）
“あんがとな 浦野すず”
アハハハ！
"Thanks, Suzu Urano!"
Hey! Keep it down!
（要一(よういち)）こりゃ！ うるさい
（すみ）フフフ…
I'm so distracted at times.
（すず）
うちは ぼーっとしとるけえ
じゃけえ あの日のことも きっと
昼間見た夢じゃったに違いない
I'm sure I was daydreaming again
August 1935
ゆんべの海 こんなじゃったのに
The sea was just here last night,
大潮の今朝ときたら こうじゃ
but now it's all gone
with the spring tide.
（すみ）アハハ！
子供だけで海渡るの 初めてじゃ
楽しいね
Crossing the sea all on our own!
First time ever! This is fun!
（要一）ええか
“草津(くさつ)のおじちゃん おばちゃん”
I'll greet our uncle, aunt
and grandma in Kusatsu first.
“おばあちゃん
おはようございます”はわしが言う
（すず）“お父さんらは
町へ寄るけえ遅うなります”
I'll say "Our parents will join us later."
（すみ）“スイカ どうぞ”
"Please have this watermelon".
ああ すみがスイカ持つ
I wanna hold the watermelon!
Quiet!
（要一）うるさい
（すみ･すず）痛っ
（要一）
ほれ 遊びよる暇なかろうが
Hey!
There's no time to play around!
（すず）お兄ちゃんは
なかなか厳しい人じゃった
My brother was quite
the stern type.
（すみ）待って うっ…
（すず）ああっ
おはようございます
Good morning...
Our parents will...
父と母は… え～
Please...
スイ… キャッ
Please have this... watermelon.
（すみ）スイカ どうぞ
（森田(もりた)）ハア…
Thanks, our ancestors will appreciate it.
（マリナ）
ありがとね お供えしようね
（イト）
ほうほう べっぴんさんじゃ
（すみの鼻歌）
You look so pretty.
（すず）おばあちゃんは毎年―
Our grandma sews us
a new kimono every year.
（すみの鼻歌）
新しい着物を仕立てて
待ってってくれんさった
（すみ）あっ！
新しい着物を仕立てて
待ってってくれんさった
（キセノ）ただいま
（十郎）やあ
Our parents joined us
after shopping
買い物へ寄った お父ちゃん
お母ちゃんもそろうたら 墓参り
and we visited our family grave.
（マリナ）どうですか？ 江波(えば)は
How's business?
（十郎(じゅうろう)）いやあ 難しいですわい
港を造るからって… のう
It's tough.
Is that so?
（森田）ほうですか
（要一）んん～
（すず）うっ うう～
う～ん
（すず）いろいろあるが―
There are ups and downs,
but it's not all bad,
being young.
ほいでも
子供でおるんも悪うはない
いろんなもんが
見えてくる気がする
I think it lets me see
different things.
（すず）ハッ…
（すず）あ…
こん… にちは…
H... hello.
あっ
あの…
Excuse me...
それ もっと
もろうてきましょうか？
Would you like some more?
Grandma.
お母ちゃん
Wake up.
The tide is pulling out.
（十郎）
ほれ はあ 潮が引いてきたけえ
（十郎）ほれ 支度せえ
（要一）う… う～ん
Get ready.
ほれ すみも
Sumi, you too.
Come on.
ほれ
放っときゃ
後で食べにきんさってよ
Leave it there, she will have it later.
So if I leave my kimono there,
うん ほしたら―
着物も置いとったら
着にきてかねえ？
Will she wear it, too?
You're so kind, Suzu.
すずちゃんは優しいねえ
"Must've been a zashiki-warashi,
a house spirit.
（すず）“そいつは 学校の先生が
言うてじゃった―”
“座敷わらしに違いない”
Teacher told me about them."
My brother explained
to me later.
お兄ちゃんが
ほう言うた その夕方―
景色も人も
優しゅう かすんで見えた
That dusk, everything looked
hazy but gentle.
（要一）はあ!?
草津へ着物を置いてきた？
You left your kimono in Kusatsu?
Swim back and get it right now!
今から取ってこいや 泳いで
ボケ！
Stupid!
（すず）痛っ！
"My ogre brother"
“鬼いちゃん”が怖いのも
忘れとったのだ
I forgot how scary my
ogre of a brother could be.
（すみ）ううー
（すず）もう
February 1938
（要一）すず もっと低う掛け
風があるけえ ハヤるで
Suzu, put it lower.
The wind could blow it away.
（すず）うん
あっ お母ちゃん
２銭ちょうだい
Mom, can you give me 2 sen?
I lost my pencil.
鉛筆 落としてしもうて
Wait for your allowance.
（要一）小遣いまで我慢せいや
You need to stop doodling.
お前が えっと落書きせにゃ
済む話じゃろうが
すみちゃん
鉛筆 替えっこしようか
- Sumi, let's trade pencils.
- No.
（すみ）いい
Suzu, is Tetsu Mizuhara
going to school every day?
（キセノ）すず 水原(みずはら)の哲(てつ)君
毎日 学校 来とる？
えっ 来とるけど
Um, I think so.
（すず･すみ）アハハ…
（女の子）
ほんま 寒いねえ
What a cold day.
（女の子）
ほんま 寒いねえ
（すみ）えい 冷(ひ)や～
（すず）ああ 冷や～
Oh, you're cold!
ハーッ
（りっちゃん）ありゃ
Oh.
It's so short!
（りっちゃん･すず）短あ
これで今週 もつかね
I hope it'll last the week.
今度は落とさんようにせんとね
Don't lose it again, ok?
（鐘の音）
"Reading"
"Math "
"Science"
（教師）今日の図画は自由画じゃ
Draw anything you want today.
You may leave after you hand it in.
提出した者(もん)から 帰ってよし
"Art"
（生徒たち）はーい
Yes, sir!
（りっちゃん）どこを描こうかね？
（すず）ねえ
What should we draw?
（教師）うん ええぞ
Nice job, Urano.
浦野 さすがじゃのう
Very impressive.
ええねえ すずちゃん
うまいけえ
I wish I could draw like you.
I'm home.
（すず）ただいま
ほいじゃ うち
コクバ拾うてくるわ
I'll gather some pine
needles for kindling.
Thank you dear.
（キセノ）お願いね
ん？
ハッ
ああ…
Umm...Mizuhara?
水原さん 早(は)よう絵 出さんと
いつまでも帰れんよ
You won't be able to go home
until you finish drawing.
I don't want to go home.
（哲）帰らん
お父とお母が のりもつまんで
飲んだくれとるし
My parents drink all day instead
of working with seaweed.
海は嫌いじゃ
I hate the ocean.
（哲）描かん
（すず）えっ…
I won't draw it.
Urano, give me your hand.
（哲）浦野 手え出せや
（すず）は？
（すず）えっ？
（哲）やる
Take it.
But I can't.
えっ ほいでも
兄ちゃんのじゃ ようけあるけ
It's my brother's,
I have plenty more.
The rabbits are
hopping about today.
ウサギが よう跳ねよる
The sea was like this when a
ship capsized at New Year's.
正月の転覆事故も
こんな海じゃったわ
If you want to draw,
then draw this stupid ocean
描きたきゃ お前が描けえや
この つまらん海でも
（すず）
水原さん 今のん どういう意味？
Mizuhara, what did you
mean earlier?
（哲）ん？ ああ
Oh, the white waves
look like rabbits hopping.
白波が
ウサギが跳ねよるみたいなが
Hey, Mizuhara,
can I give my brother to you?
（すず）水原さん
お兄ちゃん あげようか？
（哲）いらん
No way.
浦野の兄ちゃん 見たら―
All the guys run when they see him coming.
全速で逃げえいう
男子のおきてがあるけえの
ほいでも―
But still better than the idiot
who joined the Navy and drowned.
海軍の学校入って
海で溺れるアホよりゃましかものう
You're right,
（すず）ほんまじゃねえ
白いウサギみたいなねえ
they look like white rabbits.
I'm done.
できた
（哲）集めといたで
（すず）うっ ありがと
Here you go.
Oh, thanks...
（すず）ああ…
（哲）よいよ いらんことするわ
You shouldn't have bothered.
できてしもうたら
帰らにゃいけんじゃろうが
Now I have to go home.
And with a drawing like this,
こがいな絵じゃ
海を嫌いになれんじゃろうが
I can't hate the ocean anymore.
March 1940
（ラジオ:男性）東太平洋全海域に
作戦中の帝国海軍部隊は…
Imperial Navy Forces conducting
operations
in the Eastern Pacific have...
December 1941
（人々）万歳 万歳 万歳…
Hurray! Hurray!
April 1943
Pick the seaweeds over here.
（男性）森田の姪(めい)っ子
ここは はあ つんだほうがええで
December 1943
Yes.
（すず）あい
Oh,
（すみ）
あら すてきな決戦服ですこと
Lovely decisive
combat battledress.
うーん フフ…
（千鶴子(ちづこ)･すみ）うわあ 嫌ー！
That's cold!
ハアー
うん うもうなったね
You've gotten quite good. We'll
have lunch when you're ready.
ほいじゃ ええとこでお昼に
（すず）わっ はあい
Okay!
（千鶴子）遠～！
That's far!
（すず）うん？
You're going far away
to get married.
（千鶴子）すずねえちゃんは
遠くにお嫁に行ってじゃ
ほうなん？
I am?
Sumi, you're staying near.
すみねえちゃんは近いね
They say girls who hold their
chopsticks up top wed far away.
箸を遠う持つ子は
遠くへお嫁に行くいうけえね
（すず･すみ）へえ…
Really?
Where did you come from, Grandma?
おばあちゃんは
どっから来んさったん？
I came from Furue.
（イト）うん？ わしゃ 古江(ふるえ)よね
（すみ）隣の古江から草津で
そんとなじゃ―
That's just one village over.
Women who end up in Manchuria
must be using tongs.
満州(まんしゅう)やなんかへ行っての人は
火箸でも足らんね
Says Sumi, as she shifts
her grip on her chopsticks.
と言いながらも箸を持ち直す
浦野すみであった
But marrying close to home
isn't very exciting.
あんまり近いんは夢がないけえ
（戸が開く音）
（すず）ん？
（すみ）ん？
ハア！ すずちゃん すぐ帰り
Suzu, run back home!
I just got a call...
電話に呼ばれて今
何か思うたら―
A boy all the way
from Kure is here
あんた 嫁にいう人が
あんたがた 来とってじゃと
asking for your hand
in marriage.
わざわざ呉(くれ)から
Kure?
呉？
Suzu, how old are you?
（イト）すずちゃん
あんた いくつになった？
19… 満で18
I'm about 19...
Well actually, 18.
気に入らにゃ断りゃええんよ
ちいと会うてきてみんさい
You can always turn him down,
but at least go and meet him.
（イト）
すずちゃん ちょっとおいで
Suzu, come here a bit.
いずれ
あんたの嫁入りの時 思うてね
I want you to have this.
I made it for the day you wed.
直しといた
ええがに決まりゃええのう
I hope it'll work out for you.
ありがとう
Thank you.
（イト）ほんでのう
向こうの家で祝言挙げるじゃろ
The wedding will be in their
house in Kure.
うん
On your wedding night,
（イト）その晩に婿さんが―
he'll ask,
"Did you bring an umbrella?"
“傘を１本 持ってきたか”
言うてじゃ
（すず）え？
You'll answer,
"I brought a brand new one."
（イト）ほしたら “新(にい)なのを１本
持ってきました”言うんで
Then he will ask,
"Can I open it?"
ほいで“差してもええかいの”
言われたら
You must say "Yes", okay?
“どうぞ”言う ええか？
But why?
（すず）えっ なんで？
（イト）なんでもじゃ
Because you have to.
（すず）うちは大人になるらしい
I guess I'm becoming an adult.
Kure...
呉いうたら軍港のあるとこで
There's a naval port there, and
it's full of sailors, I think...
水兵さんが ようけおって
うん？
はっ えっ？ ええ？
Eh? Mizuhara?
水原さん？
It's been a while.
久しぶり
Hurry home.
（哲）早よ家行け
（すず）へっ？
Your mom made such a fuss,
everybody already knows.
（哲）お前の母ちゃん
たまげて 大騒ぎしよったで―
近所 みんな知っとるわ
あっ！ 焦った
Oh, gosh!
I thought you were the suitor!
うちは てっきり
あんたが相手かと…
アホか！
Don't be silly!
わしは兄ちゃんの七回忌に
粛々と帰ってきたとこじゃ
I just came home for my
brother's memorial.
あ… うう…
You don't know who
your suitor is?
相手 知り合い違うんか
全然
No idea.
Maybe he has me
confused with Sumi.
すみちゃんと間違(まちご)うとってんかも
Sumi is prettier than me.
すみちゃんのほうが きれいなし
（哲）ほうでもない思うがのう
I don't think so.
（円太郎(えんたろう)）これが こっちの学校へ
通うとった頃―
My son took a shine to your
daughter on his way to school.
どこかで
見初めたんじゃ思いますが
（円太郎）いやあ
お宅 捜すんも 大ごとでしたわ
It wasn't easy to
find your house.
（十郎）わしらも ３年前の
江波沖の埋め立てで―
We lost the seaweed business
to land reclamation
three years ago.
のりは やめとりましてのう
（キセノ）
もう戻ってくる思いますけえ
She should be home any minute.
はあ
（すず）ええ話かどうかは
分からんかったけど―
I can't tell if marrying
would be good.
（すず）ええ話かどうかは
分からんかったけど―
（キセノ）どうぞ
口ん中にキャラメルの味
広がった気がしたんは―
I wonder, why did I
taste caramel in my mouth...
なんでじゃったんじゃろう
It's so cold...
（すず）おお さぶ…
困ったねえ
What should I do?
They say I could turn him down,
嫌なら断りゃええ言われても
but I don't
even know if I like him or not.
嫌かどうかも
分からん人じゃったねえ
Excuse me.
（周作）あの…
Yes?
はい
道に迷うてしもうて
We lost our way.
Where is the train station?
（周作）電停はどっちですか？
（すず）こっちです
（周作）すみません
- This way.
- Thank you.
親切な水兵さんに
教えてもろうたんじゃが
A nice sailor showed us the way,
but...
（すず）ああ… ありゃ
なかなか珍奇な人ですけえ
Oh, him? He's an odd one,
you see.
山ん中おった
珍奇な女に案内されて―
They said an odd woman in the
woods showed them the way.
無事 帰れたそうな
（すず）へっ？
February 1944
（すず）うちは そんとに
ぼーっとしとったんじゃろうか
Am I so distracted that I lose
track of what's going on?
いつの間に
こうなってしもうたんじゃろうか
How did this all
happen so quickly?
"Hiroshima"
"Kaitaichi"
"Yano"
"Saka"
"Koyaura"
（すみ）どがなかね？
（すず）うん
Please close the blinds
facing the ocean.
（憲兵）これより海側の鎧戸(よろいど)を
お閉め願います
（乗客たちのせき込み）
Someone left a window open...
（すみ）どっか窓 開いとる
（駅のアナウンス）呉～ 呉～
Next stop, Kure.
（砲声）
（すず）うっ！
海軍さんの砲台の教練じゃと
The Naval battery must
be doing drills.
（砲声）
（車掌）
どうも すんません すんません
Sorry.
（十郎たち）ハア ハア…
The wood gas bus couldn't get up
the hill, could it?
（小林(こばやし)の妻）木炭バスは
上がってこれんかったでしょう
（キセノ）ああ 小林さん
（十郎）いやあ どうも
Hello, Mrs. Kobayashi.
小林さん
本日は よろしゅう頼んます
Thank you for having us.
（小林の妻）
お天気も よろしゅうて何よりで
I'm glad the weather is nice.
末永(すえなご)うお世話になります
While I am lacking in my ways, I
am honored to join your family.
ふつつか者ですが
孝行いたします
（小林の妻）周作の伯母の小林です
（すず）ん？
I'm Kobayashi, Shusaku's aunt.
I'll be your matchmaker today.
（小林の妻）仲人 務めさしていただきます
（すず）えっ…
（十郎）嫁に行く先の名字
覚えとんじゃろうな？
You do know your husband-to-be's
last name, right?
ほんまに ふつつかじゃ
大丈夫かいね
Definitely lacking in many ways.
（すみ）ほう
こんとに上がってきたんかいね
We've climbed so high!
They live on the far corner here.
（キセノ）
一番 隅っこなんじゃね ここは
（小林の妻）こちらですわい
Here we are.
"Houjo"
来んさったで
They're here!
（円太郎）このご時世
万事簡便で申し訳ない
My apologies for such a
simple wedding.
Simple suits our girl just fine.
（十郎）
うちの子はあがり症じゃし―
こんくらいがちょうどええわ
（すみ）すずちゃん
Oh no!
あれ いけん
My beautiful kimono is
all covered up.
せっかくの晴れ着が
無駄になるとこじゃ
（キセノ）あっ！ これ すず！
Suzu!
（キセノ）どこで脱ぎよんね
（十郎･すず）あ…
What on earth are you doing!
（読経）
What a feast.
（小林）
こりゃ また大ごちそうじゃ
（キセノ）ほんま この子の兄が
来れんで残念ですわ
I'm sorry her brother
couldn't come.
（十郎）
ほんま よう集めなさったのう
This is impressive.
Well, you provided us with
the ingredients.
（小林の妻）しっかり食べときよ
この家の晩の分まで
みんな出してしもうたけえ
This includes supper as well
so make sure to eat up.
This stew is delicious.
（十郎）この煮物も よう煮えとる
（すみ）よかったね
おとなしげな人で
He seems very reserved.
You're lucky.
こんな場で騒ぐ人は
おってなかろう
No one would be noisy
at a wedding.
（十郎）お前はドタバタしとったわい
（キセノ）あんたはドタバタしとったよ
Except for you.
See you when you come
home to visit!
（すみ）ほいじゃ 里帰りの時にね
（すず）ほいじゃあね
See you then!
（径子(けいこ)）また来ますけえ
I'll see you around.
Wait... who was that, again?
（すず）ええっと
誰じゃったっけ？
Now that she's here,
（円太郎）嫁も来たし―
you can rest and have
her take over.
家のことは みな任せて
安気に寝とりゃあのう
I will.
（サン）はい
お義父(とう)さん お義母(かあ)さん
末永うお世話になります
Mom, Dad, it's an honor to be
part of your family.
（サン）いえのう こちらこそ
The honor is ours.
I have a bad leg so,
私ゃ 足を痛めてましてのう
よろしゅうね すずさん
I'm counting on you, Suzu.
はい
Of course.
（円太郎）すまんのう
Thank you.
径子に炊かすと
いつも焦がすんじゃ
Keiko always burns the pot.
はあ ありゃあ お嫁に
行きんさった お義姉(ねえ)さんでしたか
Right! She's the daughter
who got married.
ん？ ああ…
（周作）軍艦の照射訓練じゃ
（すず）わあ
Naval ships are doing
search light drills.
（すず）
うちは一体 どこへ来たんじゃろう
Where have I ended up?
ハア…
（周作の鼻歌）
お布団 ありがとうございます
Thank you for setting out the futons.
Sure.
（周作）うん
（鼻歌）
Oh, Suzu?
ああ すずさん
（すず）はい
Yes?
Did you bring an umbrella?
（周作）傘は持ってきとるかいの？
はい… 新なのを―
Yes, I have.
１本…
It's brand new.
（周作）ちょい貸してくれ
Can I borrow it?
よっ…
ほれ
Here.
いやあ 腹減ったのう
You must be hungry.
何じゃ まだ渋かったか？
Were the dried
persimmons too bitter?
昼間 何も食べとらんかったでしょ
You didn't eat at the wedding.
ちゃんと口から食べんさるけえ
安心しました
I'm glad you can eat
with your mouth.
（周作）ぐっ！
ああ… 安心せえ 安心せえ
今 種まで飲みました
Yes, don't worry. I even swallowed
the seed.
ちゃんと口からの
With my mouth.
あの… うちら どこかで
先(せん)に会いましたか？
Have we met before?
（周作）うん 会うたで
We have. Don't you remember?
あんたは覚えとらんか
すみません
I'm sorry.
I tend to be distracted and
unaware of my surroundings.
うちは ただでさえ
ぼーっとしとるもんで
（周作）昔から そがいながった
You haven't changed at all.
ほいで昔も
ここへ ほくろがあった
I also remember your
beauty mark.
井戸はね 下に隣保(りんぽ)で
共同のんがあって ほいで…
We share the neighborhood well.
"To Yoichi Urano"
"Houjo..."
（すず）北條(ほうじょう)…
"Suzu Houjo"
あっ…
（すず）あの…
Excuse me.
ここって呉市の
何町の何番ですか？
What might be the address
of this house?
（円太郎･周作）ええ？
（サン）はあ？
"Kami-Naganoki cho 808"
（すず）あっ はい
Of course!
（円太郎）ほいじゃのう
We're off.
Have a nice day.
（すず）いってらっしゃい
この辺は皆 海軍さんに
お勤めなのかしらねえ
Everyone around here seems
to work for the Navy.
ハア…
Mrs. Houjo?
（堂本）北条さん
北條さん
（すず）あっ はい
Ah, yes!
（すず）配給当番？
"Rationing duty"?
Remember, these two are
always at it.
（サン）ここと ここは
いつも これじゃけねえ
Nice to meet you.
お世話になります
- I'm Chita.
- I'm Kariya.
（知多(ちた)）知多です
（刈谷(かりや)）刈谷です
There you go again!
ほれ また
ちゃんと量っとるじゃないの
I'm measuring properly
You're eyeballing it!
目分量いうんじゃ あんたのは
- No I'm not.
- It's unfair!
（刈谷）いいや
（知多）不公平になるで
It is not!
（刈谷）ならん
（知多）まったく
（刈谷）何ね？
- Unbelievable.
- What is?
You and your ways.
あんたのそういうとこが
いけんのでえ
What ways?
（刈谷）どこが
Haha, I'm young, don't worry!
（すず）アハハ… 若い若い
（刈谷）ありゃ
It's gonna fall!
あんた 落ちんで
（すず）うわっ
ありゃあ
Oops!
うわあ
Ouch...
（知多）あいたたた…
（すず）す… すみません
I'm so sorry.
（軍人）
甚だ 大であること―
That possibility cannot
be ruled out.
指摘せずにはおられません
もし焼夷(しょうい)弾が落下してきた場合―
If incendiary bombs come down,
必要となるのは 一に機転の利いた
処置でありますが これは…
first you must timely counter
and neutralize...
Come closer!
It's so chilly in here.
もっと寄ってえやあ
この席は寒いけえね
（知多･刈谷）うんうん
（すず）はい
This has become my daily life.
（すず）
こんとなんが うちの毎日になった
March 1944
That's Keiko's dress from
when she was younger.
ああ それ
径子の娘時分の服
It goes in the storage.
それも物置じゃね
それ着て 婿さんなりよる人と
連れ立って歩いとったんよ
She wore that on dates with her husband.
それ着て 婿さんなりよる人と
連れ立って歩いとったんよ
（すず）うわ～
They'd go to the cinema,
fancy restaurants, and exhibits.
映画見たり 洋食屋さん行ったり
博覧会行ったり
（すず）わあ
モガだったんですね お義姉さん
She was quite the modern lady.
Those were the days.
（サン）
まだ そがあな世の中じゃったねえ
When Shusaku was in the
fourth grade,
周作が４年の時―
the "disarmament for peace"
平和のための軍縮で
軍艦 造れんようになって
treaty shut down
warship production.
My husband and neighbors lost
their jobs. It was a hard blow.
うちの人も この辺でも
ようけ失業しんさって
大ごとじゃったんよ
But Keiko found a job and
a husband all on her own.
径子は まあ ああいう子じゃけえ
仕事も自分で決めて
婿さんも自分で見つけて
Well! I'll work just as hard!
さあ ほしたら うちも
負けんよう頑張って働かんと
We thought those
times were tough.
大ごとじゃ思うとった
あの頃は
（住民）万歳！
How I miss those days now.
（サン）大ごとじゃ思えた頃が
懐かしいわ
（戸が閉まる音）
（すず）あっ こんにちは
Hello.
I'm home.
ただいま
（すず）
あっ おかえりなさい お義姉さん
Welcome back.
あっ！
ハア… さえん
Humdrum...
（すず）ん？
Humdrum? How? Rice is
such a luxury now!
“さえん”なんて 今日び お米は
貴重品じゃないですか
（径子）あんたのことじゃ
I'm talking about you!
広島の子じゃいうけ
さぞや あか抜けとる思うたのに
I expected a sophisticated
city girl from Hiroshima.
What's that rag you're wearing?
何ね そのツギハギだらけの
もんぺは！
（晴美(はるみ)）お豆さん 煎りよってん？
Are you roasting beans?
Hello Harumi.
ありゃ 晴美ちゃん
いらっしゃい
Mommy is mad about
everything lately.
お母さん 機嫌悪いことやら
ようけあるけ
So I stay quiet.
晴美 おとなしゅうしとるん
（すず）すみません
（サン）ほうね
I'm sorry, it's all I've got...
（すず）今は こんなもんしか
Then make one right now.
作れ！ 今すぐ
Also, that rice isn't a gift,
it's for me and Harumi.
あと そのお米はお土産と違う
私と娘の分じゃからね！
Keiko...
（サン）ほいで？ 径子
（径子）聞いてや お母ちゃん
But, Mom!
（すず）はてさて 弱ったね
Oh, dear. What should I do?
痛っ！
Ouch!
ほりゃ また 違う違う
Not again, not like that!
No one will marry you
if you don't do it right.
そんとにヘタクソじゃ
お嫁に行かれんで
That's fine. Then I won't marry.
ええもん 行かんもん
う～ん…
ううー
What's it like at the waist...?
えーっと 腰んとこは…
I see.
ああ なるほど
ううーん
うん？
I undo the seams and cut.
Put them together and sew.
これをほどいて 再び裁つ
合わせて縫う
Put in a waistband and I'm done!
ゴムを通せば 出来上がり
よしよし
I'm Harumi Kuromura.
黒村(くろむら)晴美です
I'm Suzu Houjo.
北條すずです こんにちは
すずさん ひもちょうだい
Can I have some string?
あっ これでええですか？
Will this do?
（時計の鐘の音）
Oops.
（すず）おっと
Are you going shopping?
（径子）すずさん お使い？
はい 配給所へ
Yes, to get rations.
I'll go. Hand me your
ration coupon and wallet.
私が行ったげよう
配給切符とお財布 貸し
ほうですか お願いします
Are you sure? Thank you.
（戸が開く音）
Welcome home.
おかえりなさい
Stop. I'll do it.
もうええ 私がやるよ
（すず）は？
Hey, Mom!
ねえ お母ちゃん
よっこら… はいはい
I'm coming. What is it, dear?
（サン）何ね？
（径子）おつゆの実じゃけどね
What should we do for soup?
（すずのため息）
（あくび）
Just the two of you?
（円太郎）おお 径子と晴美が
来とるんか ２人か
Welcome home, Dad.
（径子）おかえり お父ちゃん
Make yourself at home, Keiko.
（円太郎）
まあ ゆっくりしていけや
（径子）うん
What a surprise.
My big sis didn't burn the rice.
珍しい
姉ちゃんが炊いたメシにしては
あんまり焦げとらん
Shusaku!
（径子）こら 周作
（周作）いたたたっ
Excuse me.
（すず）あの お義姉さん
おかげさまで
このとおり 着物が直せました
Thank you,
I was able to fix my kimono.
（周作）ああ～
（径子）うん？ いいえ
My pleasure.
Our mother has a bad leg,
お母ちゃんの足の具合
悪いからいうて―
and we brought someone like
you to a place you don't know.
あんたみたいな子を 知りもせん
土地へ連れてきてしもうて
If only I could've stayed.
私が ずっとここへおりゃ
よかったことなんよね
Suzu. Why don't you
go home to Hiroshima?
すずさん あんた広島 帰ったら？
What?
えっ？
That's a good idea.
（円太郎）そりゃええ
（サン）うん…
（戸が開く音）
"Hiroshima Castle, Suzu Urano"
（すみ）ただいま
I'm home.
フウ くたびれた
I'm so tired.
Welcome home.
（キセノ）おかえり
It's eight already.
ああ もう８時じゃねえ
今日は また多いね
That's quite a pile.
おっ？ これ みな千人針か
These are all
thousand-person-stitch sashes?
Yes. Sumi, make sure to
stitch each one.
ほうよ すみ 後で刺しといてね
（すみ）うん
Okay.
Suzu! Enough sleeping! Get up!
（キセノ）こりゃ！ すず
ええかげん 起きい
は… はい！
Y... yes!
It's time for dinner.
（キセノ）ほら もう晩ご飯しよ
ああ 焦った
呉へお嫁に行った夢見とったわ
Oh gosh. I dreamt I
married a man in Kure.
（すみ）アハハ…
（すず）ああ…
Are you awake now?
（キセノ）目え覚めたかね
（すず）はい
ほいで お義姉さんが
広島帰ってええ言うてくれんさって
My sister-in-law said
I should think about going
back to Hiroshima.
（キセノ）うん
I was puzzled at first.
何のことじゃろ思たんじゃけど…
（すず）あっ！ 里帰り
（径子）ああ？
Oh, to visit my family!
ほしたら
お義父さん お義母さんも―
Then my in-laws apologized
for not letting me come
visit sooner.
“今まで気が利かんで
悪かったのう”
“２～３日ゆっくりしておいで”
言うてくれんさって
They told me to relax
for a couple of days.
お義姉さんも
あんたが それでええいうなら
よかとじゃない
Uh, if that's what you want,
isn't that nice?
（すず）って
Did you write to Yoichi?
（十郎）
そういや 要一にハガキ出したか？
うち？ 出した
I did.
まだ 何も返ってこん
I haven't heard from him,
though.
（すず）うちへも？
（すみ）うん
- You too?
- Nothing.
まあ 遠いし
He's stationed far away.
お兄ちゃん 筆不精じゃし
And he doesn't write much.
Suzu might've written
the wrong address, too.
すずが宛先
間違うとるかもしれんし
（すみ･キセノ）うんうん
（２人）お風呂 お風呂
Bath time!
すみちゃんは挺身(ていしん)隊は どんな？
How's the volunteer corps?
I'm getting used to it.
Don't I smell like machine oil?
（すみ）だいぶ慣れた
うち 機械油臭いじゃろ
It must be a dangerous job.
（すず）
危ない仕事なん？ 大変なね
It's not as cold as harvesting
seaweed.
ほいでも のりの仕事ほど
寒ないし ええこともあるよ
There are good
things about it.
A handsome high-ranking officer
slips me his meal tickets.
美男子の将校さんが
こっそり食堂の食券くれたりね
Oh my!
ありゃあ
I think I just accidentally
learned some Army secret!
思いがけず
陸軍の機密 知ってしもうた
How about you? Do you like Kure?
すずちゃんこそ どうなん？
呉って ええとこ？
I don't know yet.
There's so much to learn.
うーん 覚えることだらけで
まだ何とも
（すみ）あっ！
（すず）え？
うち 今…
Maybe I did just tell you a
Navy secret!
思いがけず海軍の機密に
触れてしもうたみたい
（すず）な… 何？
（すみ）もう寝よ
- What?
- Good night!
Suzu?
（すみ）すずちゃん
（すず）ん？
Yeah?
You're getting a bald spot.
（すみ）ハゲが できとるよ
（すず）えっ!?
Bye Suzu! I'm off to work.
（すみ）じゃあね すずちゃん
いってまいります
Emergency policies
start next month.
（十郎）決戦非常措置じゃけえ
月が替わったら
短い旅行も制限になるいうけ
Even short travels will
be restricted.
Take care.
（十郎）元気でのう
（すず）うん
I will.
Time for me to go
to the women's association.
さあて うちも
婦人会の内職へ行かんと
What? You're leaving, too?
えっ お母ちゃんも出かけるん？
"Railroads fight too"
Dad gave me an allowance.
（すず）
お父ちゃん お小遣いくれた
Goodbye.
（すず）さようなら
Goodbye, Hiroshima.
さようなら 広島
"Tickets Sold Out"
（すず）あれ？
What?
（十郎）ほいで 戻ってきたんか!?
That's why you came back?
I feel bad for the Houjo family.
向こうの家の人らが
気の毒になってくるわ
くう～
（すず）あっ ただいま
I'm home.
April 1944
（すず）
お義姉さんは ずっとおりんさる
Keiko stayed all along.
Mommy, can I borrow the ink?
（晴美）お母さん
ねえ すずり 貸して
What for?
（径子）何ね 晴美
I wanna use it.
（晴美）ねえ 貸して
Suzu?
（径子）ちょ… すずさん
晴美に何言うたん
What did you tell Harumi?
Can I take care of the
community notices?
回覧板 もう回してええですか
Sure.
（サン）どうぞ
I'll go now, then.
いってきます
She's been a bit off since
coming back from Hiroshima.
広島から帰ってきてから
ずっと ああじゃが…
Let her be. She's still a child.
放っとき まだ子供なんよ
（すず）
ほいじゃあ よろしくお願いします
Thank you for your time.
（晴美）ねえねえ
- Please!
- I said no!
（径子）ダメじゃ言うたら
（晴美）筆貸して ねえねえ
Lend me the ink brush.
You don't need it.
（径子）あんたは いらんでしょう
そんなん
（すず）あっ… おかえりなさい
Welcome home.
Picking herbs?
（周作）草つみよったんか
（すず）
はあ 晩ご飯のおかずに思うて
Yes. For tonight's supper.
I see.
（周作）ふーん
（すず）ここいらのタンポポは
みな白いんですねえ
Dandelions here are white.
Are they different in Eba?
（周作）江波のんは違うんか？
おっ 黄色いのもあるで
Here's a yellow one.
（すず）あっ
（周作）うん？
What?
It might've traveled far.
（すず）
遠くから来とってかもしれんし
You seem sad. Are you homesick?
何じゃ 元気ない思うたら
広島が恋しゅうなったんか
No, I'm not.
（すず）なっとらんです
（すず）う…
（周作）ああ
Look, over there.
見てみい ほれ
今日は航空母艦もおる
They're aircraft carriers. Maybe
it's the Hiyo and the Junyo.
飛鷹(ひよう)と隼鷹(じゅんよう)かのう
They're so big.
（すず）大きいです
Those little ones are
destroyers.
（周作）
あこらの こまいんは みな駆逐艦
There's a U-boat from Germany.
ドイツから来たＵボートもおるし
あの普通の船みたいなんは
潜水母艦で…
That ship is a submarine tender.
Look, there's a white-eye.
ほれ メジロが飛んどるで
（すず）はあ
Over there.
（周作）あれじゃ あれ
（周作）ほれ
（すず）見よります
I can see.
（すず）うう…
（周作）ああ…
（すず）あっ 周作さん
ありゃ 何ですか？
Shusaku, what is that?
Is that a ship?
船ですか？
That's the Yamato,
大和(やまと)じゃ
the world's greatest warship,
東洋一の軍港で生まれた
世界一の軍艦じゃ
born from the Orient's
greatest shipyard.
（すず）はあ…
あれにも人が乗っとるの？
There's people on it, too?
Yes.
（周作）ああ
About 2,700 people.
ざっと2700人
（すず）2700人…
Two thousand...
and seven hundred?
That's right.
Let's welcome them to Kure.
そうじゃ 呉へおかえり
言うたってくれ すずさん
（すず）はあ～
They cook for 2,700 people
on that boat every day?
あんとな所で
そんとにようけの人らに―
毎日 ご飯作っとるん？
（周作）すずさん
- And do laundry?
- Hey, Suzu.
（すず）洗濯は… あっ！
（周作）ああっ うわっ
（落ちる音）
うう…
す… すみません 大丈夫でしたか？
I'm sorry. Are you all right?
Yes.
いや ケガはないか？
あ～あ
Are you hurt?
あ…
Suzu, stress will only
make you lose more hair.
のう すずさん
気にしよったら
ハゲは余計にひどうなるで
So you knew...
バレとりましたか
Can I borrow the ink brush?
I want to paint Suzu's head.
ねえ 筆貸して
すずさんの頭に墨塗ってあげるのん
I said no!
いけんちゅうたら
You'll stain everything black.
そこら中 真っ黒にするでしょうが
あんたは
（晴美）ええ～
（すず）ああ…
Soon, Keiko left and went back
to her late husband's family,
（すず）そのうち お義姉さんも
お嫁入り先へ帰っていきんさって
so I thought--
All right! now it's my
turn to cook!
さあ ほいじゃ うちがご飯の支度を
と思うた時にゃ―
But by then, rationing
became much worse.
配給がだいぶ減っとった
May 1944 "Sold Out: Next
Delivery Unknown"
Four dried sardines for three
meals for a family of four.
いわしの干物４匹で
一家４人の３食分
It's still better then just
being given vegetable leafs,
まあ 菜っ葉だけの日より
ましではあるし―
and maybe I can buy
some soy pulp.
こけえ並んどったら
そのうち卯(う)の花も買えるじゃろ
I see.
ああ なるほど ああ
Violets,
スミレ ハコベラ スギナ
stellaria, field horsetail.
Dandelions, dried sardines,
and soy pulp.
タンポポ カタバミ
いわしの干物 卯の花
Potatoes, sweet potatoes, flour
and pickled plum pits.
馬鈴薯(ばれいしょ) お芋 小麦粉
梅干しの種
うーん
さつまいもを切りて 蒸す
Cut and steam a sweet potato.
スギナは軽くゆで
水にさらして刻む
Boil and chop some
field horsetails.
Mix them with flour
and form a flat disk.
小麦粉をお芋とスギナに
つき混じて 平たく丸める
お昼ご飯の出来上がり
And lunch is ready!
径子らがおらんと静かなね
It's so quiet without Keiko.
Dry the leftovers for
another day.
（すず）余りたるは
干して保存すべし
さあて まだまだ
Moving on...
お米を５倍の水で薄め
おかゆさんにすべし
Use extra water for thin
rice porridge.
Add potatoes and let it simmer
for ten minutes.
馬鈴薯 乱切りを加え
さらに10分
ハコベのざく切りを加う
Then add chopped stellaria.
Cook daikon rinds and dandelion
roots with soy sauce and sugar.
大根の皮 タンポポの根―
千切りにして
砂糖としょうゆで煮る
Add dandelion leaves and soy
pulp then let it simmer.
タンポポの葉のざく切りを加え
卯の花に混ぜ さらに炊く
大根は薄く切りて塩にてもみ
カタバミを混ぜる
Finely slice and salt daikon,
then add yellow wood sorrel.
Boil pickled plum pits in water.
梅干しの種と水を鍋に入れ
煮立ったら いわしの干物を加う
Add the dried sardines
and stew while basting.
蓋をせず 煮汁をかけつつ煮る
Finish it off with salt.
仕上げに塩で味を調う
Mrs. Kariya taught
you this recipe?
（サン）ほうね 刈谷さんに
教えてもろうたんね
Rice rations were halved
so I made sweet potato porridge.
お米の配給が半分しかのうて
お芋の多い おかゆさんで
Good job.
何の
ほいでも 明日は
任してつかあさい
I'll do better tomorrow.
The loyal samurai Kusunoki
devised
忠臣 楠木(くすのき)公が
ろう城に耐ゆるため―
発明したる食糧増量の法
the "food increase
recipe" during a siege.
First, toast and
brown some rice.
まず米をよーく煎る
Add triple the amount of water
and gently simmer the rice.
３倍の水を加え
弱火でじっくり炊き上げるべし
Saving rice and energy
must go hand in hand.
節米しても燃料を無駄にしては
つまらない
ここは大日本帝国の利器
火なしコンロに任せて―
Leave it to the fireless stove
of the Great Empire of Japan!
朝を待つ
Let it sit overnight.
ゆうべの残りの煮魚の汁に
スミレを加え―
Add miso and violets to
yesterday's sardine stew.
みそを入れて ひと煮たち
ご飯は再び火にかけ
沸騰させておく
Reheat rice on the stove.
Samurai Kusunoki's special,
"Nanko Meshi" is served!
出来上がり
これぞ 楠木公ゆかりの楠公飯(なんこうめし)
This one is for Father-in-law.
こっちは お父さんのお弁当に
（周作）おお…
今朝は えろうご飯が多いのう
We have lots of rice today.
The grains are so puffy.
メシ粒が膨らんどる
I've never seen rice
cooked this way.
こがいな炊き方があるんね
- Yes.
- Let's eat.
（すず）はい
（一同）いただきます
（一同）うーん？
- We're off.
- I'm so sorry.
（周作）いってきます…
（すず）すんません
Lord Kusunoki must have been
quite bold and remarkable
（サン）あれを喜んで
召し上がる楠木公は―
ほんまの豪傑なんじゃろうねえ
to enjoy meals like that.
Yes, I agree.
ほうですねえ
（警報）
June 1944
（男性）警戒警報 発令
Air raid warning!
（警報）
Air raid alert!
（男性）空襲警報 発令
There's nothing on the radio.
Is Shusaku off to work already?
放送は何も言うとらん
周作は はあ職場へ向こうたんか？
Yes.
（すず）はい
（円太郎）まあ
Estimates of the enemy's range
敵の予想航続力からすりゃ
初回は九州がええとこじゃ
puts only Kyushu in
danger for now.
ここらで慌てて
山へ逃げ込むこたあ… あっ
No need to run to the
mountains yet.
（すず）ひゃっ
It's only a blackout.
（円太郎）ただの停電じゃ
（すず）ああ
（女性）あんた 落ちんさんなや
Don't fall now.
They are removing buildings.
（周作）建物疎開かのう
市内に広う防火帯 造るんじゃと
They need firebreaks.
I see.
（すず）はあ
Not around here, but
in the city.
（周作）まあ ここいらは
心配いらんのんじゃろうが
That's terrible. I hope they can
find a place to live.
大変ですね
皆 引っ越し先は
見つかるんじゃろうか
あ… すみません
Thank you.
You're welcome.
（径子）どういたしまして
（すず）うん？
I have plenty of firewood.
My house was torn down.
薪(たきぎ)なら なんぼでもあるけえ
私んがたも取り壊しになってね
Oh no.
（すず）ありゃあ
The family will move
to Shimonoseki.
ほいで 家ごと
下関(しものせき) 行くことになってね
（円太郎たち）ええ？
So I left my husband's family.
ええ機会じゃけえ 離縁してきた
What?
（円太郎たち）はあ!?
Don't worry. I'll find
a job and work.
心配ご無用
仕事見つけて 働きに出るけえ
There will be more of us now.
（円太郎）
入る人数が多なったんじゃけえ
Like this?
（すず）うん こうですか？
（サン）うんうん
Yes!
July 1944
（砲声）
I heard them over Mt. Haigamine.
（知多）昨日は灰ヶ峰(はいがみね)の上でも
やっとったね
Big guns even up there?
（刈谷）
あげなとこにも大砲来たんじゃね
Things are getting
more precarious.
（堂本）いよいよ物騒な
（すず）ありがとうございました
Thank you for helping us.
What a fine bomb shelter.
（サン）まあ ええ防空壕(ごう)が
出来上がったこと
It is.
（すず）ええ
（周作）よし
So admirable of him to build
this shelter
（サン）残業続きなんに
張り切りんさったけえね
even with
all that overtime.
The pillars and tatami mats from
Keiko's house were a godsend.
姉ちゃんがたの
柱やら畳があって助かったのう
周作 これ あんたがここに？
Shusaku. Did you
place this here?
It's nothing.
（周作）何じゃ？ 何でもないわい
Let's clean up out here.
さて 表もちっと片づけるか
よいしょっと
Can I have some of this
dirt for our field?
周作さん この土
ちいと畑へ持ってってもええ？
Sure, take it. Just be careful.
（周作）おう 持ってけ 持ってけ
気いつけての
So this is where you've been.
（すず）ありゃ
ここへ おりんさったん
うん お船見よった
Yes. I'm looking at ships.
（すず）よいしょ ハア…
There's a lot of ships today.
今日はまた ようけおってじゃね
大和が２つおる
I see two Yamato ships.
One of them is Musashi.
１個は武蔵(むさし)じゃ
I see lots of warships,
but no aircraft carriers.
戦艦は ようけおってのに
航空母艦はおらんねえ
I see.
へえ
あっ あれは利根(とね)よ
後ろに砲塔がないじゃろ
That's the Tone. She has
no rear turrets.
She's an aircraft cruiser.
航空巡洋艦よ
Really?
へえ すっごいわあ
よう知っとるねえ
That's amazing. You know so much.
Yeah, he taught me.
うん お兄さんに教えてもろうたん
なるほど
うちも ちょっと教わったよ
I see. I also learned a
thing or two.
That's a destroyer.
（すず）駆逐艦
（晴美）うん
（すず）あっ
なんか こまいんが来よるが
I see small ones.
That's a motor launch.
（晴美）内火艇(ないかてい)じゃね
I'll teach you something too.
へえ ほいじゃ うちもお礼に
Look at that big cloud.
（すず）大きな雲じゃろう
（晴美）うん
It's an anvil cloud.
（すず）カナトコ雲いうてね
（晴美）うん
It causes heavy rain.
（すず）大雨になります ハァ…
（晴美）えっ！
Shusaku!
（すず）ひゃあ 周作さん
Take everything into
the shelter.
（周作）
とりあえず その辺のもんを壕へ
（２人）ああー
Thanks.
（周作）おお すまん すまん
ハア…
（すず）ハアー
あっ やります やります
No, I can do it.
So you like warships?
（すず）軍艦がお好きなんですね
（周作）え？
Did you teach Harumi
about warships?
晴美さんから聞きました
ああ
晴美に教えたんは わしじゃない
ひー坊じゃ
I didn't teach Harumi.
Hi-bo taught her.
He?
（すず）ひ？
（周作）うん
Yeah, Hi-bo loves battleships.
軍艦好きの ひー坊じゃ
いつか すずさんにも会わしたる
You'll meet him one day.
（すず）このヒサオいう人？
Is his name Hisao, as
etched here?
Yes.
（周作）うん
（すず）あっ
I can't believe I'm here,
doing this with him.
（すず）こんなことしとる
うち この人と
Good.
（円太郎）
よし 小降りになったのう
Let's go while it's
only a drizzle.
今のうち 帰ろうや
Father...
（周作）あの…
You're a married couple.
It's nice that you get along.
まあ 夫婦なんじゃけえ
仲ええことは結構なことで
（径子）ええ ええ
夫婦仲ようて結構なことじゃない
Isn't that nice. Two couples
getting along so well.
２組そろうて
Keiko...
（円太郎）径子…
They used to measure their
heights together as a family.
（周作）家族そろうて仲よう
背比べしとったんじゃのう
Wait, did Keiko's husband...
（すず）もしかして
そのお義姉さんの旦那さんいう人…
He was too frail to be drafted.
I guess he was way too skinny...
せっかく兵隊に行かんでもええ
細い体じゃったんに
細すぎたんかいのう
お父ちゃんが
工廠(こうしょう)に再就職できた時―
When my father was rehired
by the Navy Arsenal,
Keiko went to buy a watch for
him, that's where they met.
姉ちゃん お祝いに
時計買いに行って―
そこの若旦那と知り合(お)うたんじゃ
"Kuromura Watchmaker"
嫁に行って 若夫婦２人で
店 新しゅうして
They got married and
they renewed the store.
But Keiko, with her temper,
（サン）ほいじゃが
径子は あの性格じゃけ
didn't get along
with his family.
ご両親と折り合わんでね
婿さん のうなった後―
When her husband died,
店をどうするかで
やねこいことになって―
they fought over the business.
But in the end...
ほいでも結局
建物疎開で何ものうなった
The building removal
took everything away.
Hisao is the heir
of the Kuromura family.
久夫(ひさお)は黒村の跡取りじゃけえ―
Her son was taken to
Shimonoseki.
下関へ連れてかれて
さすがに こたえたようじゃわ
Even for Keiko,
that was hard on her.
みんなが笑(わろ)うて
暮らせりゃええのにねえ
I wish we could all
live happily.
Me too...
ほんまですね
はっ
ちょっと 野菜見てきますけえ
I need to check on the garden.
It took several months for me
to find that out about her.
（すず）そんなことと分かるまでに
うちは何か月もかかってしもうたよ
ほんま
ぼーっとしとるもんじゃけえ
That's how
distracted I can be...
That's Yamato.
あれが大和
That's Tone.
こっちが利根
ひゃっ あっ…
あ… あの… えっと
うちは その…
Sir. I was... just...
"Military Police"
うちはただ 遠くへ越した子に
船の絵を送ろう思うただけで…
I just wanted to send
a drawing to my nephew...
（憲兵）この女の家はここか？
Does this girl live here?
（サン）け… 憲兵さん
（径子）ええ!?
The military police?
海岸線と艦影を写生しよった
She was sketching
shorelines and ships.
That's espionage!
間諜(かんちょう)行為じゃ
こんな こげな顔して―
She may look innocent,
どがいに悪辣(あくらつ)かつ狡知(こうち)にたけた
計画を巡らしておるか分からん
but who knows what nefarious
plots she is scheming!
Her husband is a two-bit clerk
（憲兵）この女の夫は―
海軍軍法会議所の
下っ端録事じゃげなの
at the navy
court-martial office.
Has she attempted
to access military secrets?
女が隙を見て軍事機密に
目を走らせおる恐れはないか？
Has she sent coded
transmissions?
暗号通信しよる気配はないか？
Does she have a random
number table?
女の持ち物に
乱数表を見たることはないか？
Is there anything suspicious
regarding her background? Well?
背後関係をにおわせるものは？
うん？ どうか？
We will not arrest her today,
but keep a close eye on her.
今回は 検挙立件は手控えるが
監視の目は常に光らすように
After all, a daughter-in-law
was a stranger before!
嫁というても
所詮は他人じゃからのう
ええい
（時計の鐘の音）
（周作）ただいま
I'm home.
The laundry is still outside.
何じゃ？
洗濯物 干しっぱなしで
Shusaku...
（サン）あっ 周作 それが…
The military police
investigated Suzu and...
（サン）すずさんが憲兵さんに
（周作）はっ？
Suzu, come with me.
すずさん ちょっと来んさい
（すず）えっ？
It's so small, you won't be able
to draw the shoreline.
そんだけ小さきゃ
海岸線も描けんわ
すずさんは
絵描くんが好きな人じゃったか
Suzu, since you love to draw,
can you draw me sometime?
今度 一度 わしを
描いてくれんか
I don't know if I can
draw you well...
（すず）それは…
上手に描かれんかもしれんし
（周作）ハア…
Suzu involved in espionage...?
すずさんが間諜か…
Shusaku, you were lucky...
（径子）周作 あんたは ええよ
We couldn't be rude
to the MPs...
私ら 憲兵さんに申し訳のうて
笑うに笑えんし
We had to hold back
our laughter.
Which only made it funnier.
（サン）こらえたら
余計おかしゅうなるし
（周作たち）アハハハ！
ご覧のとおり熱中すりゃ―
This girl forgets everything
when she's focused on something.
すぐ周りが
目に入らんくなる子じゃのに
Acting humble made her look
cunning and what not.
神妙にしとるのが また無駄に
知恵者に見えんさったらしゅうて
She's so clueless, she thought I
work as a store clerk.
（周作）こん人は６時に帰るけえ
ロクジじゃと思うとった人で
Suzu a spy? Those Army
MPs are idiots!
どんな機密を狙うんか
陸軍のバカ憲兵が
なんか分からんが
つられて おかしゅうなってきた
I don't understand,
but it sounds funny!
（笑い声）
I wish we could all
live happily.
みんなが笑うて
暮らせりゃええのにねえ
Me too...
ほんまですねえ
I'm home.
（円太郎）ただいま
（径子）あっ お父ちゃんか
お父ちゃんにも聞かせたろ
Dad's home! Let's tell him, too!
（笑い声）
Am I the only one who
doesn't find it funny?
（すず）素直に笑えんのは
うちだけか
（笑い声）
（円太郎）ほう ほうほう
August 1944
（すず）戦争しよってもセミは鳴く
Even in war,
cicadas cry and butterflies fly.
チョウチョも飛ぶ
（女性）ハア… 暑いのに
"Sugar rations end in August"
No more sugar?
（すず）ありゃ お砂糖もかね
We thought the war
would hit home soon
６月の空襲騒ぎの時は もう―
when all the air raids
happened in June...
すぐ目の前にやって来るか
思うた戦争じゃけど
Wonder where it is now?
今はどこで どうしとるんじゃろう
（晴美）あっ
（すず）ありゃ！ ああ
Ouch.
（晴美）いたたた…
I'm sorry, Harumi.
晴美さん ごめんごめん
大丈夫
ありこさん 見とってん
I'm okay. I was
looking at the ants.
（すず）ほう
I wonder where they're going...
どこまで続いとるんじゃろうかねえ
（すず）うん…？ うん…
（晴美）うん
（すず）うん うん うん…
（晴美）うん…？
（すず）うん…？
ん？
ああ！
今や お砂糖は貴重品じゃのに
（晴美）
あ～！ ありゃ～
Sugar is precious right now!
ああ！
今や お砂糖は貴重品じゃのに
うわっ ああ ああ～…
（すず）あっ
（晴美）うわっ
We need to hide it
from the ants.
ありこさんに見つからんとこ
隠さんと
But where?
ほうじゃけど どこへ？
ん？ ん…
ど… どうしたん？
What's wrong?
We thought putting it
（すず）水の上なら ありこさんも
近寄れんじゃろ思うたのに
in the water would keep
the ants from it.
（晴美･すず）うわあ！
これ持って
ヤミで買うてきんさい
Here, buy some at the
black market.
（すず）いつもと違う道
Roads I usually don't travel.
Eat up!
（子供）召し上がれ
We're supposed to be low on
everything.
（すず）売るもんなんて
何もないはずじゃのに
What are all these
people doing here?
なんで こんとに人が…
What?
ええ？ ええ… ええ
This is a fine rice from Taiwan.
（女性）こりゃあ 台湾米
とっときのじゃけえね
（客）ふん
I could get some Japanese rice,
too.
（女性）何なら内地米も
手配できるけえ…
（すず）おお～
I thought we were not supposed
to grow watermelons now.
（すず）ありゃ スイカは
畑で禁止のはずじゃが
はあ～ 何でもある
They have everything here.
ははあ
戦争前の夏休みみたいじゃねえ
It's like summer breaks
before the war.
Sugar is 20 yen.
（店主）砂糖１斤20円
は… 配給の50倍以上？
That's fifty times the
ration price!
今 買わんと まだ高(たこ)うなるで
The price will only go up now.
（すず）お義母さんのヘソクリと
今月の生活費 合わせても25円
With mother's money and this
month's budget,
I only have 25 yen.
Eeny, meeny, miny, moe...
かきのたね
"Buy or Not Buy"
Will sugar cost about 150
yen in the future?
どうね 今にお砂糖が
150円くらいになって
キャラメルやなんかも
100円でも買えんくなって
A box of caramel could
cost more than 100 yen.
Maybe three pairs of socks
will cost 1,000 yen.
靴下じゃって―
３足買うたら 1000円にも
なることになりゃせんかね
そんとな国で 生きていけるんかね
How will we survive in a country like that?
あっ…
Wha...?
ええ？
ほいで ここは どこね？ 一体
Where am I?
（女性）ん？ 長ノ木(ながのき)？
海軍墓地のある？
Naganoki? The naval cemetery?
Wait, that's Nagasako.
あ… ありゃ 長迫(ながさこ)かあ
Isn't it over there?
（女性）ああ あっち
（女性）こっちよね？
It's that way.
（すず）ハア…
（リン）あっ ごめん
I'm sorry.
It's okay.
（すず）いえ
Watermelon?
（リン）スイカ？
（すず）はあ
Yes.
（リン）キャラメル
（すず）はあ
Caramel?
Yes.
（リン）迷子？
（すず）はあ
You're lost?
Yes.
Even though you're a grown-up?
（リン）大人なのに？
どっから来んさったん？
Where did you come from?
Naganoki.
長ノ木
Miss, no one will give me
directions
おねえさん
誰も帰り道 教えてくれんし
and everyone
smells very nice.
みんな あんとに ええ匂いさせて
ここは竜宮城か何かかね？
Am I in a fairy tale palace?
For Naganoki,
長ノ木なら角を曲がって
郵便局まで下りて ほいで…
you turn that corner and go down
to the post office...
Wait here.
待っとってね
ねえさん ちょう 教えて
Madam, I have a question.
（においを嗅ぐ音）
Go straight and turn right
when you pass the post office.
ここ行って これを出て
ほいで 郵便局の先の角を
右へ曲がるんと
Thank you so much.
ありがとうございます
People around here are not
well informed.
（リン）ここいらの人は
皆 不案内なけえね
ほとんどが よそ者じゃし
この門を出もせんし
Most of us aren't locals and
we stay within these gates.
Are you also from South
Hiroshima? Near the ocean?
あんたも広島の南の…
海のほう？
I am. But how did you...?
ほうですけど なんで？
Your accent...
言葉で
Are you from Eba?
ほう 江波とか
From Kusatsu.
（リン）うん 草津とか
Kusatsu!
草津
I had watermelon at my grandma's
every summer.
毎年 おばあちゃんがたで
スイカ食べたねえ
We were poor, so I always ate
the rinds people left behind.
うちは貧乏じゃったから―
人の食べた皮ばっかり
かじっとったよ
I met a kind person once though,
いっぺん 親切してもろうて
赤いとこ食べたねえ
so I finally could have the red flesh.
遠い昔じゃね
It was a long time ago.
You draw very well.
ほいでも あんたの絵 上手じゃけ
眺めとったら
Looking at them... can you...
あの…
Sure! I'll draw
whatever you want.
お安い御用じゃ
他にもあったら言うてつかあさい
Mint candy and bracken dumpling!
はっか糖 わらび餅
Mint candy.
はっか糖
And ice cream with
wafers on top.
あと アイスクリーム
ウエハーがついとって…
Wafer?
ウエハ？
What? You've never
been to a cafe?
知らん？
きっちゃ店 行ったことないん？
Rin!
（女性）リン！
Stop playing around so much.
あんまり油売りなや
Sorry, I have to go.
ごめん やっぱし もう行かんと
I'll come back another time
with more drawings.
ああ
ほいじゃ 今度描いてきますよ
Don't.
ええよ こんなとこへは
さいさい来るもんじゃない
You shouldn't come back here.
えっ
フフフ… また迷子になるでえ
You'll get lost again.
（径子）遅いわ 市場行ったいうけ
帰り道 間違うとるんか思うたわ
What took you so long?
Did you get lost or something?
はあ
お義姉さん
Keiko, what is an ice cream with
wafers in a cafe?
ウエハーのついた きっちゃ店の
アイスクリームいうたら―
どんなもんですか？
You don't know?
何じゃ 知らんのね
Well. It's sweet and cold.
そりゃ あんた 甘(あも)うて 冷(ひよ)うて
You eat it with a
crispy cracker.
サクサクのおせんべいみたいんで
すくうて食べて
Ah, wonderful...
はあ そりゃもう
（すず）あっ それ…
Wait...
ああー
久しぶりに甘いもんの話
しようたら
Thinking about desserts
makes water taste sweet.
ただの水も甘う思えてくるねえ
（すず）ああ…
September 1944
It's still very hot.
（すず）まだまだ暑い
Mrs. Houjo,
（知多）北條の嫁さん
あんたに電話
you got a phone call.
はい うちにですか？
Yes? A phone call for me?
Ah, this is what he wants.
あっ これこれ
The heat is not letting up.
ハア… 暑い暑い
恥をかくのは周作なんじゃけえね
あんたが そがな格好で出歩きよったら…
You'll embarrass Shusaku
dressed like that!
Still some time,
let's take a walk.
（軍人の話し声）
How goes it with the GKF?
（軍人）それでＧＫＦの様子は
どうだったかね
Things are quite laid back.
（軍人）のんびりしたもんです
Good! Let's have a cold beer, then.
（軍人）そうか
"Kure Navy Court-Martial Office"
あっ
Shusaku, I've brought
your notebook.
周作さん
帳面をお届けに上がりました
What?
（周作）えっ？ あ…
フフ…
あっ… ああ！ すずさん
Suzu? You're very pale,
are you okay?
えらい白いが大丈夫か？
I guess I look funny, right?
へ… 変ですかね
No. I'm happy if you're okay.
いや 元気ならええ
Let's go then.
ほいじゃ 行くか
Go? What about work?
えっ？ お仕事は…
I used the excuse that
（周作）急ぎでもないのに
わざと帳面持ってこさしたんじゃ
you needed to bring me
that notebook.
街へ買い物に出て
楽しかった言うとったろう
You had fun shopping in
the city, right?
What's the matter? Are you ill?
うん？ どうしたんだ
やっぱり具合…
I don't want you seeing me
smiling ear to ear!
しみじみ ニヤニヤしとるんじゃ
（すず）ほう～
（周作）映画でもと思うたが
I wanted to take you to
the cinema, but...
（２人）ハア…
I guess a big ship is
back in port.
（周作）大きい船が
帰ってきたとこなんかのう
Sailors need their break.
ここは まあ譲らんとの
We'll go another time.
残念なが またにするか
Suzu?
すずさん？
A classmate of mine from
elementary school
（すず）小学校の同級で
水兵さんになったんがおって
became a sailor.
What if I bump into him?
会うたら どうしよう思うて
普通に挨拶したらええが
Then you just say hi.
（すず）昔 知っとった人に
今 会うたら―
I might wake from this dream
if I met someone from my past.
夢から覚めるとでも
思うんじゃろうか うちゃ
（周作）夢？
Dream?
Changing my name and
moving was hard for me,
住むとこも名字も変わって
困ることだらけじゃが―
but you're so kind to me.
And I've made friends.
ほいでも周作さんに
親切にしてもろうて
お友達もできて
うん 今覚めたら面白うない
I don't want to wake up because
I'm happy to be who I am today.
今のが ほんまのうちなら
ええ思うんです
（周作）なるほどのう
I see.
The past and the paths we did
not choose,
過ぎたこと 選ばんかった道
みな 覚めて終わった夢と
変わりゃせんな
they're like a dream.
すずさん あんたを選んだんは―
Suzu, choosing to marry you,
多分 わしにとって
最良の選択じゃ
was the best
decision of my life.
I'm worried that
you've lost weight.
ちいと痩せたようなけえ
心配じゃがの
I suppose I've lost my
appetite lately.
そういや 最近 食が進まんような
（周作）ほう
（すず）あ…
（すず）あっ！
（周作）えっ？
（すず）ああ！
（周作）あっ！
Here. Eat for two people!
（径子）はい ２人分
"Clinic"
You had a lot for breakfast.
This should be enough.
朝 余計に食べたんじゃし
こんくらいで ええよね
（すず）はあ…
Eating for only one after all.
（すず）やっぱり１人分
（兵士）入港準備 前進微速 赤20(ふたじゅう)
Ready port entry. Slow ahead.
Reduce 2 knots.
December 1944
ヨーソロー 微速前進
赤20 ヨーソロー
Aye, sir. Slow ahead.
Reduce 2 knots.
Aye-aye, sir.
I'll go ask for you.
ほしたら 頼んでみたげるけえ
（哲）おう
Thanks.
（晴美）あれ？
（すず）あっ
Hello?
（晴美）わあ！
ほんまもんの水兵さんじゃ
A real sailor!
井戸のとこで ばったり会うて
We bumped into each
other at the well.
水原 哲
軍艦青葉 乗組です
I'm Tetsu Mizuhara, an
Aoba crewmember.
Isn't Aoba a Class A cruiser?
（晴美）青葉いうたら甲巡(こうじゅん)ですね
（哲）おっ
Stop, Harumi.
（径子）これ 晴美
（哲）ハハハ…
You're tanned even in winter.
うわあ 冬なんに
真っ黒に日焼けじゃねえ
ほいで うちへは
お風呂つかりに来んさったんかね
So you're here to take a bath?
"Bath shore leave"
means free time,
（哲）ああ 入湯上陸いう名の
自由時間です
and I had nowhere to go.
行き先も まあ あれなんで
同郷のすずを頼ってお邪魔しました
So I thought of Suzu,
a friend from back home.
Thank you for taking
care of Suzu.
皆さんには
すずが世話んなりよります
Suzu was only good at drawing
and making seaweed.
すずは昔から
絵と のりすきしかとりえがのうて
She must be quite useless here.
ここじゃ ただのぼんやりでしょう
I'll take her off your
hands anytime!
まあ 遠慮のう言うてくださりゃ
連れ帰りますわい
ハハハ… うっ！
キザも大概にせえ
Stop being so cocky!
And don't call me by my first name!
“すず すず”呼び捨てしくさって
うん？
じゃ どう呼びゃあええんか
What? I can't call you
Urano anymore.
もう浦野じゃなかろうが
What?
えっ…
Suzu, you can't hit a sailor.
すずさん 水兵さんに乱暴は…
（すず）うう～
（笑い声）
ハハハ…
ハッハハ…
What's so funny?
（すず）何か面白いかね
You. You're so normal.
面白いでえ
お前は ほんまに普通じゃのう
This is delicious!
うまい うん うまい
It's nothing special.
お粗末さまじゃが
極楽 極楽
This is heaven.
おーい すずも入れや
Suzu, come join me!
Are you crazy?
アホか！
（哲の歌声）
Suzu, where's the lamp?
すずさん ランプはどこかいの
（哲の歌声）
あっ 確か壕の中に
I think it's in the shelter.
ほうか
Right...
I'm gonna be a sailor
when I grow up.
晴美も将来 水兵さんになる
（哲）おっ そりゃええのう
（サン）はい
That's great.
いただきます
Thank you.
What do you say?
（径子）ご挨拶は？
Good night.
（晴美）おやすみなさい
（哲）フフ おやすみなさい
Good night.
There's nothing like
being on dry land.
ああ 陸(おか)はええですのう
（サン）ほいじゃ うちは
I'm going to bed.
How is Aoba?
青葉は どがいなですかのう
マニラで負傷して
ようよう戻ってきました
We came back from
Manila with the wounded.
It's a great ship,
ええ艦なのに またしても
活躍も沈没もせずじまいじゃ
but it's without victory
or defeat, again.
Feeling left behind, alive,
のう 周作さん
while others have
already died...
死に遅れるいうんは
焦(じ)れるもんですのう
Makes me feel anxious...
水原さん
Mr. Mizuhara, with my father
away on duty,
父が夜勤で戻らん今夜は
わしが家長じゃ
I'm the head of this family.
I'm sorry, but I can't let you
sleep in this house.
申し訳ないが あんたを
ここへ泊めるわけにはいかん
うん？ ありゃ？
What?
I asked him to sleep in
the storeroom.
納屋の２階で寝てもろうた
That was quite a sight.
いや 珍しかったで
I can't remember ever seeing you
being so assertive.
あんたでも
強気の時があるんじゃのう
はあ
I readied the bed warmer.
Take it to him.
ほれ アンカつけたけえ
持っていってあげんさい
Talk to him. It may be the
last time you see him.
ほいで ゆっくり話したらええ
もう会えんかしれんけえのう
I'm sorry about the room.
ごめんね こんなとこへ
ハハ… つり床に比べりゃ
極楽じゃ
It's heaven compared
to a hammock.
ほれ 積もる話じゃ
寒いけえ 足入れえ
We have lots to
talk about. Come.
Okay.
（すず）うん
Here. This is for you.
ほれ お土産じゃ
Really?
ありゃ
（哲）羽根ペンにすんか
（すず）うん
Are you making a pen?
There...
（哲）よし
It works.
（すず）わあ 書ける書ける
（哲）書けるのう
It looked like a heron,
but I saw it in the South.
サギに似とったが
会うたんが―
南の海じゃったけえのう
I didn't know they migrated.
（すず）サギは海を渡るんかいねえ
Me neither.
（哲）のう 江波じゃ年中―
Back in Eba,
they just stood in the river.
川へ立っとるだけじゃったにな
There were lots in Eba.
ああ 江波にゃ
ようけおったねえ
ああ… どうもいけん
思ったように描けん
No, I can't draw it very well.
That's hard to believe.
お前でも そんたな時あるんか
Wait. You haven't
drawn in a while?
ひょっとして
久しぶりなんか？ 絵描くのが
Well...
まあ
That drawing of white
rabbit waves...
あの絵 あの波のウサギ
Yes, I remember.
ああ あれ
あの後 大変じゃったしのう
It caused a lot of trouble.
えっ？ そうじゃったん？
Really?
You forgot?
（哲）忘れたか？
（すず）えっ？
Our teacher entered it
into a contest.
先生が あの絵
広島市の大会へ出してしもうて
そこで屈指の評判になって
わしゃ ほんま困った
Everyone loved that drawing,
and I didn't know what to do.
They all thought I drew it,
when actually the real artist...
わしが描いたこと
なっとったけえのう
ほんとの手柄は
お前なんにのう
Was you.
（すず）フフ…
ハッ…
Suzu, you are so warm,
すずは ぬくいのう
Suzu, you are so soft,
すずは柔いのう
甘いのう
and sweet.
Mizuhara...
水原さん
I've been waiting for
this moment forever.
うちは ずっと
こういう日を待ちよった気がする
You coming for me...
こうして あんたが来てくれて
You finally being here...
But I...
こんなに そばにおってのに
うちは…
ああ！
I'm so angry at him! It
boils my blood!
ほんまに うちは
あん人に腹が立って仕方がない
ごめん ほんまに ごめん
I'm sorry, I'm so sorry.
I understand.
（哲）あん人が好きなんじゃの
You love him.
I do.
（すず）うん
あ～あ
たまげるくらい普通じゃのう
You're surprisingly normal.
I'm sorry.
ごめん
You still get angry and
apologize for ordinary things.
（哲）まるで
当たり前のことで怒って―
当たり前のことで謝りよる
You want to stay?
ほんまに連れて帰らんでええんか
I thought you were forced to get
married and needed help.
無理に嫁にされて
困っとったん違うんか
No...
（すず）ううん
Then it's all good.
なら ええ ハハ…
Is he four years older?
４つ上かいのう
（すず）周作さん？
Shusaku?
He's the same age as my brother.
（哲）死んだ兄ちゃんと同い年じゃ
Our family was poor, so he chose
a tuition-free naval academy.
うちが貧乏じゃったけえ―
兄ちゃんは タダで行ける
海軍兵学校入った
But when my brother died,
I signed up to join the Navy.
兄ちゃんが死んだけえ
わしゃ海軍入った
They were ordinary choices,
全部 当たり前のことじゃのに―
but somewhere along the way,
I derailed from the ordinary.
わしはどこで人間の当たり前から
外されたんじゃろうかのう
That's why...
じゃけえ ここで
普通でおる すずを見て安心した
I'm relieved to see that
you haven't changed.
わしは英霊呼ばわりは
勘弁じゃけえ
So don't revere me
when I'm gone.
Smile when you think of me.
わしを思い出すなら
笑うて思い出してくれ
I want you to stay ordinary and
sane in this world
お前だけは最後まで この世界で
普通で まともでおってくれ
until the end.
Suzu.
（哲）すず
（すず）うん？
お前 べっぴんなったで
You're beautiful.
アホか
You idiot!
アハハ… ハハ…
（すず）ほんまに
こまい頃から あんたには
Since childhood,
I've never been able to tell you
how I really feel.
肝心なことが言えん癖が
ついとんじゃもん
"Tetsu, thank you for
staying alive."
（僧侶）
いまだ万歳(まんざい)の人身(にんじん)を受けたりと…
"Army Private First
Class Yoichi Urano"
February 1945
（イト）ハア…
Welcome home.
（一同）おかえり お兄ちゃん
They sent us a single rock
instead of his bones.
（すず）じゃけど 骨の代わりが
あげな石ころ１つとは
This perplexed Sumi, so...
あんまり ちんまいんで
すみちゃんなんか…
Is this Yoichi's brain?
（すみ）お兄ちゃんの脳みそ？
Was her guess.
…と間違えたくらいじゃ
どがあな兄さんなんか
What was he like?
They called us up in the
cold for this?
寒い中 呼びつけられて
アホらしい
あの要一が
そう簡単に死ぬもんかね
There's no way Yoichi is dead.
People are gone just like that.
（すず）
あっけのう 人は おらんようになる
Our voices can't reach
those no longer with us.
姿が見えんようになれば
もう言葉は届かん
Shusaku.
（すず）周作さん
I wanted to thank you.
こないだは
ありがとうございました
えっ？
水原さんと話する時間もろうて
For giving me the time
to talk to Mizuhara.
It's nothing.
いや…
ほいでも周作さん
夫婦ってそんなもんですか
But doesn't marriage
mean more to you?
I forced you to marry me.
わしが無理言うて
嫁に来さしてしもうたけえ
And yet you've never shown
your angry face to me.
わしには見せんくせに
あげな怒り顔
（すず）なっ…
今 見しとるでしょうが
I'm showing it to you now.
（ブレーキ音）
Oh, so now you're mad?
ほう 怒っとるとは知らんかった
You need to pay attention!
（すず）そりゃ注意散漫じゃ！
Oh yeah?
（周作）ほう～
ほいで今日にかぎって
ホゲた靴下はいとってんですか
Why did you have to wear
socks with holes today?
The one you sewed
last night were too tight.
すずさんが ゆうべ繕うたんは
足が入らんことなっとったんじゃ
Wear something else!
他のも あろう
Could you sort out
that argument at home?
（男性）お二人さん そりゃ
今せにゃいかんケンカかね？
You're going the
wrong way again.
（周作）また道 間違えよってから
こっちじゃ！
I know.
（すず）分かっとります
Our house is toward Mt.
Haigamine.
（周作）うちはあっち
あの灰ヶ峰の方角じゃ
I said, I know!
（すず）分かっとりますて！
It snowed a lot that winter.
（すず）その冬は雪が多うて―
I couldn't wait for
spring to come.
春が待ち遠しかった
More vivid than indigo
（すず･晴美）♪「空の神兵」
March 19th, 1945
The big blue sky
Opens right up
With white roses
adorning everywhere
Like wallpaper,
going on forever.
～♪
アハ なんじゃあ
Don't worry.
No teacher will scold a
well-behaved child like you.
晴美さんは おとなしいけ
先生も叱ってんないんよ
Really? School isn't scary?
ほんま？ 学校 怖ないん？
It's not. You'll make friends,
too.
うん 今はお友達おらんでも
I didn't know anyone here at
first,
ほれ うちもここへ来た時は
一人ぼっちじゃったけど
but now everyone
is my friend.
すぐ みんな 仲ようしてくれたし
うちのお母さんも？
My mommy, too?
（ラッパの音）
（すず）あ…
（晴美）うん？
（すず）え～…
Well...
What?
うん？
（ラッパの音）
（戦闘機の音）
（砲声）
（晴美）あっ
（銃撃音）
（すず）あっ 防空頭巾
Watch your head!
（晴美）うう…
（すず）晴美ちゃん
Harumi!
（砲声）
（晴美）うわ… うう…
（すず）ああ…
If only I had paint and
paper with me...
今ここに絵の具があれば
Damn it, what am I thinking!
…て うちは
何を考えてしもうとるんじゃ
（円太郎）おーい！
Hey!
What are you doing?
何しとるんか！
陰へ入れ 早よ伏せえ
Stand back! Take cover!
（警報）
Welcome home!
おかえりなさい
おいおい
今頃 空襲警報かいのう
That air raid alert is way too
late. Watch out for shrapnel.
じっとしとれ
砲弾の破片に当たるで
（破片が当たる音）
（円太郎）あたっ！
Ouch!
Can you hear that?
（円太郎）鳴らしとるのう
（すず）え？
Our 2,000 horsepower engines
sound wonderful.
わしらの二〇〇〇馬力が
ええ音鳴らしとる
That's why we work day and night
at the factory,
わしらが日夜 工場(こうば)で働くんは―
あれを歩留まりよう
仕上げるためじゃ
to improve their efficiency.
ハア…
We've come a long way from the
Type 91500 horsepower engines.
九一式五〇〇馬力から始めて
ここまできたかのう
We strive to improve our skills,
♪ いそしむ技術にこもれるは
a light of hope for world peace.
♪ 世界平和の光なり
A unified
determination and goal...
♪ 全力集中一念に
（晴美）ねえ 敵は何馬力なん？
What about their engines?
What's their horsepower?
ねえ 敵は何馬力…
（倒れる音）
（すず）お義父さん!?
Mr. Houjo?
（砲声）
Air raid all clear!
（男性）空襲警報 解除
（すずと晴美の泣き声）
そりゃ 夜勤明けじゃし
この陽気じゃし
I know you worked all night,
but how could you fall
asleep during an air raid?
ほいでも空襲中に
地べたで熟睡って あんた…
There, there.
まあまあ
I was so scared.
びっくりしたあ
We caught many fish in
Kure that day.
（すず）その日 呉では
魚がようけ取れた
It's tiny.
（晴美）ちっさ
It'll be big if you
draw it bigger.
絵に大きゅう描いたら
大きゅうなるけえね
（笑い声）
（警報）
04:50 hours, March 29th, 1945
警報発令 警報発令
Air raid alert! Ready
air raid gear!
防空服装 火の始末
戸や ふすまを外す
Put out all fires! Remove
sliding doors!
Grab survival kits and
head to bomb shelters!
以上を終えたら
非常袋を持って防空壕へ
Air raid alarm all clear.
（男性）空襲警報 解除
うっ いけん 生煮えじゃあ
It's still raw...
Poor Mrs. Kariya,
（堂本）気が重いねえ
March 31st, 1945
（知多）あんには
旦那さんも戦死しとってのに
She lost her husband in the war.
今度は17の息子さんまでじゃけねえ
Now her 17-year-old is
being drafted.
（すずたち）おめでとうございます
Congratulations...
（警報）
22:10 hours, April 1st
防空服装 整え
火の始末はよし
Ready air raid gear!
Remove sliding doors!
戸や ふすまを外す
Survival kits...
（すず）防空用具… あ～！
（周作）あたっ
I can't see anything.
（径子）もう 暗(くろ)うて見えんわ
（すず）あたっ
（猫の鳴き声）
（径子）ひゃあ ごめん
Oops! Sorry!
Whose cat is that?
（すず）どこの猫？
（警報）
23:45 hours, April 5th
（周作）うーん
（あくび）
I'm tired of sirens.
警報 もう飽きた
（あくび）
Never seen that before...
（すず）初めて見た
（シャッター音）
April 6th, 1945
17 large enemy aircraft
（ラジオ:男性）
ヒトマルヨンサン 敵機 大型17機
currently above Mt. Tsuburayama.
May 5th, 1945
福山(ふくやま)上空 福山砲戦中
Engagement ongoing. 30 aircraft
approaching from southeast.
後続目標
徳島県南東部に30機
Heading towards Kure.
呉方面に向かいつつあり
（男性）空襲警報 解除
Air raid alarm all clear.
あ～あ
（ラジオ:男性）５日午前
敵 大型125機 来襲
May 5th morning -- Air raid. 125
large enemy aircraft attacked.
Damage to Hiro Naval Arsenal
広(ひろ)工廠および11空廠の…
and Air Arsenal No. 11
was very limited.
I'm home.
（周作）ただいま
Good. You're safe, Shusaku.
あっ 無事じゃったかね 周作
Where's Father?
父ちゃんは？
- Not home... yet.
- I see.
いえ まだ…
ほうか
Suzu, it's boiling over.
すずさん 噴いとるで
（すず）あっ
ああ…
You're so small.
すずさんは こまいのう
You're small even
when you stand.
立っても こまいのう
（すず）あっ… 何ですか？
What is it?
（周作）何もない
Nothing, You're small.
That's all.
こまいけえ こまい言うただけじゃ
（すず）大丈夫ですよ
お父さん きっと
Your father will come
home safely.
（周作）軍服じゃ
（すず）えっ？
My military uniform arrived.
What?
It's wrapped up there.
（周作）風呂敷の中身じゃ
From the 15th,
I'll be a Chief Petty Officer.
15日付で法務の一等兵曹になる
I'll go to Navy training and
won't be back for 3 months.
今度は軍人じゃから
海兵団で訓練される
三月(みつき)は戻れん
（すず）その後は
戻ってこられるんですか？
Will you come back
after training?
I think so.
（周作）多分
But you'll be okay, Suzu.
大丈夫かのう すずさん
You're small,
こがいに こもうて細うて
but you can protect this house
all on your own.
誰も男がおらん このうちを
守り切れるんかのう
無理です 絶対 無理！
I can't! That's impossible.
I'm sorry. I lied.
ごめんなさい ウソです
I'm so fond of you.
うち あんたが好きです
But I might forget your face
after 3 months without you.
ほいでも 三月も会わんかったら
顔も忘れてしまうかもしれん
Suzu...
すずさん
じゃけえ この家で待っとります
That's why I'll wait
for you here.
この家におらんと周作さんを
見つけられんかもしれんもん
Because I don't know
if I could find you otherwise.
Sunday, May 6th
Tuesday, May 8th
May 10th: One air-raid alert.
May 11th: Two alerts.
May 12th: No warnings.
May 13th: Three air raid
warnings only.
May 14th
Will you not forget me if you draw me?
描いたら忘れんか？
（すず）
あっ ありゃ たとえ話で
It was a figure of speech.
With you, it's possible.
いや すずさんなら分からんし
Let me see. Am I handsome?
どれ どがいな男前に描けたんか
I can't show you.
It's top secret!
いけん いけん
こりゃ 重要機密じゃ
May 15th
じゃ いってまいります
I'm off.
Take care.
いってらっしゃい
I'll walk you half way.
（径子）周作
途中まで一緒に行こうや
（周作）ああ
Thanks.
Military uniforms are so handsome!
（晴美）軍服 カッコええね
The house suddenly feels larger.
なんか急に
家が広うなった気がするねえ
（配達員）ハア ハア…
June 21st
（配達員）北條さんに
（径子）うん？
For the Houjo's.
ハア ハア ハア…
I thought he would've been
admitted to a hospital nearby.
（サン）てっきり広の
共済病院か思うたら ほうね
（すず）どうりで
見つからんわけですね
No wonder we couldn't find him.
（径子）腹と頭を
やられたらしいんじゃが
He's hurt but he'll be
discharged soon.
もう退院間近げな
お父ちゃんに
時計の修理を頼まれた
Dad asked me to
repair his watch.
It's a good chance to visit
the Kuromura family tomorrow.
ええ機会じゃし 下関の黒村んがたへ
行ってこよう思うんよ
明日にでも
Where my brother is?
えっ お兄さんとこへ？
I'll get ready.
（径子）支度せんと
晴美も？
Can I come?
- What about school?
- Don't worry.
（晴美）学校は？
（径子）ええ ええ 行っても
土いじって体操するだけじゃろ
All you do is dig stuff
and physical training.
The hands of girls
（女性たち）♪「勝利の日まで」
can also work for our country.
We are all...
（径子）ああ こりゃ時間のかかる
This will take forever.
（晴美）ハア…
I'll get the tickets.
Can you take Harumi to Dad?
（径子）切符買うとるから―
晴美をお父ちゃんのお見舞いへ
連れてってくれるかね
（晴美）へ？
All right. Let's go.
はあ ほいじゃ 行こうか
晴美ちゃん
Can we visit the Navy?
（晴美）海軍の中 入れるの？
Sure.
（すず）うん…
Don't worry.
何じゃ 弱気な
Push comes to shove,
use your bamboo spear!
いざとなりゃ 自慢の竹やりが
あるじゃないですか
You idiot! I'm not scared
of ex-in-laws!
アホか 向こうの親が
怖いんと違うわい
いや 元気がないけえ てっきり
You seemed worried so...
Bamboo spears won't be
useful anyhow.
いうか竹やりで どうせえと…
Is Shimonoseki far?
（晴美）下関いうて遠い？
Yes.
（すず）うん
Farther than Hiroshima?
（晴美）広島より遠い？
Way farther.
（すず）ずっと遠いよ
Over there?
（晴美）こっち？
You have to stay quiet okay?
（すず）病院じゃけえ
おとなしゅうせんとね
（レコードの音楽）
（晴美）敵性音楽っていうのん？
（兵曹）シーッ
Is this enemy's music?
心配かけたのう
I'm sorry I got you worried.
I've been unconscious.
I hear it's June already.
長いこと意識がのうて
もう６月なんじゃのう
I'm glad you're alive.
とにかく何よりでした
We're gonna ride the train
and see my brother.
晴美 今から汽車ん乗って
お兄さんとこ行くん
ほうか
まあ 早いほうがええの
Is that so? The
sooner the better.
What ship were you in?
ねえ 何の船に
乗っとりんさったん？
Auxiliary minesweeper No.16.
（兵曹）掃海特務艇 第十六号じゃ
（晴美）ふーん
ここへおったら
いろんなことが分かる
I've heard many things here.
Hiro Arsenal closed down
広廠も閉庁したし
and there are rumors that we'll
be merged with the Army.
海軍自体が陸軍に
吸収されるいう うわさもある
Did you know that Yamato sunk?
すずさん 大和が沈没したげな
Yamato?
大和が？
ああ せっちん詰めにされて
敵前へ躍り出てしもうた
Backed into a corner, she went
out with her guns blazing.
The Seto Inland Sea is
no longer ours.
わしらの海じゃ
のうなってしもうたけえ
（すず）ほいじゃ
波のウサギも もう…
Which means the white
rabbit are...
- What?
- Nothing.
（円太郎）うん？
（すず）いえ
That's why I suggested,
（円太郎）じゃけえ
わしが言うたんじゃ
黒村のご両親がたへ
晴美を疎開さしてもらえと
that Harumi should go live
with the Kuromuras. It's safer.
ここよりゃ なんぼか安心じゃろ
So that's why Keiko was...
それで お義姉さん
Suzu, can we go over there?
（晴美）ねえ すずさん
あっち見に行ってええ？
I want to tell my brother
which ships I saw here.
何の船がおりんさったか
お兄さんに教えてあげるん
Not sure if we can see
them from there.
（すず）ええ～ 見えるかねえ
Just a peek!
（晴美）ちいとだけ ちいとだけ
We can't see anything.
（すず）見えんねえ
（警報）
What should we do?
Can't go home...
（すず）ありゃいけん どうしよう
家までは戻れんし
どっかに公共防空壕か何か…
Need to find a public
bomb shelter.
えっ？
Are they really coming?
（女性）ほんまに来るんかね？
（女性）ここんとこ
空振りばっかりじゃったけえねえ
We've had series of
false alarms.
（男性）マルキュウフタサン
徳山…
0923 hours, enemy aircraft
sighted southeast of Tokuyama.
敵機 大型
おおよそ20機(ふたじゅっき) 呉へ向かう
About 20 large aircraft
heading to Kure
（女性）
あーあ 今度はほんまに来よった
They're coming,
すみません 入れてもらえますか
Can you let us in?
Come quickly.
早よお入り
（男性）退避 急げ！
Evacuate! Run!
すずさん 怖い
I'm scared.
大丈夫 ほれ
We'll be okay. Look.
（晴美）あっ お母さん
That's Mommy.
（すず）うん
ほいじゃ こっちは？
And who's this?
Me...
（晴美）晴美
Your mommy is always with you.
晴美ちゃん お母さんと一緒じゃ
You're not from around here,
right?
（女性）この辺の子じゃないねえ
We're visiting from Naganoki.
病院の見舞いに 長ノ木から
そりゃあ 間が悪かったのう
Bad luck, huh?
Cover your ears! Open your
mouth!
（女性）来た！ 耳塞げ
口開けえ 目飛び出るで
Or else your
eyes will pop out!
It's so hot...
（晴美）暑い
（すず）うん 我慢
Hang on...
（爆発音）
（悲鳴）
（すず）う… ハア…
（せき込み）
（晴美のせき込み）
Excuse me. Can we
have some water?
（すず）あの…
お水もろうてええですか？
（女性）ああ…
ありがとうございました
Thank you very much.
Did we miss the train?
（晴美）汽車 もう出たかね
Maybe the train is
waiting for people.
（すず）汽車も動けんけえ
待ってくれとりんさるよ
Okay.
（晴美）うん
（半鐘とサイレン）
あっ！
ああ～ 何も見えん
I can't see.
うーん ううーん
Are you all right?
（消防士）大丈夫か？
We're fine!
（すず）はーい
Dud bombs may actually
have delayed fuses.
不発弾は―
（サイレン）
時限爆弾の可能性があるけえ
早よ逃げえよ
Evacuate now!
Yes! Thank you for
your hard work!
はあ 頑張ってつかあさい
ねえ すずさん
Hey Suzu?
Will you draw my
brother some time?
今度 晴美のお兄さんも
描いてね
Craters of unexploded
bombs are small...
（軍人）不発弾の漏斗孔(ろうとこう)は
かなり小さく―
According to latest reports,
the enemy uses these bombs...
最近の
民防空戦訓速報によれば―
敵は投下爆弾の
一部に…
（すず）
はっ！ 危ない！ 晴美ちゃん
Watch out, Harumi!
（晴美）あっ！
Not again, not like that!
（イト）ほりゃ また 違う違う
No one will marry you
if you don't do it right.
そんとにヘタクソじゃ
お嫁に行かれんで
She warned me many times,
but somehow I did marry...
（すず）思えば
何べんも言われたが―
行けんことはなかったな
Watermelon.
スイカ わらび餅 はっか糖
Bracken-dumplings.
Mint candy.
I wish there had been a ditch
to jump into.
あの道に溝でもあったら
飛び込めたのに
I held my bag with my left hand.
左手に風呂敷包み
I held Harumi with
my right hand.
右手に晴美さん
If only I had it the
other way around.
反対じゃったらよかったのに
If I had at least run barefoot,
せめて ゲタを脱いで走っておれば
坂の向こう
We may have made it over the
hill... What was there anyway?
坂の向こうは…
That's the Tone and that's the Hyuga.
あれは利根 こっちは日向(ひゅうが)よ
Look, Mommy. It's the Yamato.
お母さん 大和がおってじゃ
（径子の泣き声）
She...
（すず）この人…
She looks so much like Shusaku.
ほんま 周作さんに似とりんさる
You were there with her.
（径子）あんたが ついて…
あんたが ついておりながら！
How could you let this happen?
（すず）ごめんなさい
I'm so sorry, Harumi.
ごめんなさい 晴美さん
I'm so sorry, Keiko.
ごめんなさい お義姉さん
Murderer.
（径子）人殺し
You killed her!
人殺し！
- Give her back.
- Stop, Keiko!
（円太郎）やめえ 径子
（径子）晴美を返せ！
（サン）
そろそろ お豆腐の配給じゃ
It's time for the tofu rations.
She's not herself right now.
She didn't mean what she said.
あの子も動転しとって
本気で言うとりゃせんよ
We're glad at least
you survived.
うちらは
あんたが助かっただけでも―
よかった思うとるんよ
Really?
（すず）そうかな
誰でも この世界で そうそう
居場所は のうなりゃせんのよ
You can't lose your place
in this world so easily.
Rin?
（すず）リンさん
（リン）ねっ
Where was my place in
that moment?
あん時 うちの居場所は
どこにあったんじゃろうか
あの板塀
いくらか板が抜けとったはず
Those fences should've
had some gaps.
If we had jumped through...
爆風に乗って
あそこへ飛び込めば
あの向こう あの向こうこそ…
To the other side, to
the other side...
（警報）
June 28th
やれやれ またかいね
Not again.
Ignore the siren.
They won't come.
この音は来やせん
寝とれ 寝とれ
This house survived just fine?
この家は何ともなかったんですね
Yes. Don't worry.
（サン）ほうよ 心配いらんで
よかった
I'm glad.
I lied.
（すず）ウソだ
I wonder...
あの人 家を壊してもらえて―
Was it easier for her to leave?
With her house all destroyed.
堂々 この町を
出ていけたんじゃろうか
Don't strain yourself.
（径子）無理せんでね
July 1st
（円太郎）まあ 大儀かったら
職場で休ませてもらうわい
I'll take a break at
work if necessary.
（径子）いってらっしゃい
Be safe.
The sun is out.
（サン）ありゃ 日が差しとるよ
I'll hang the bandages to dry.
（径子）包帯 表へ干しとこうかね
（ラジオ:男性）
中国地区 防空情報
23:50. Chugoku air raid
information.
23時50分
敵機は広島湾に２(ふた)目標
Enemy aircraft in Hiroshima Bay.
周防灘(すおうなだ)に２目標
Can you get up?
起きられるかね すずさん
（すず）ええ 大丈夫です
Yes.
23:58 hours. Enemy aircraft
circling Kure and Hiroshima.
（ラジオ:男性）23時58分
敵機は呉および広島付近を―
数機旋回中のもようなり
（サン）ほれ
23:58 hours. Enemy aircraft
circling Kure and Hiroshima.
（サン）あっ…
（径子）ハア…
（サン）ほうほう
ようけ来とってじゃ 姿は見えんが
There's so many of them,
but can't see anything.
（径子）ああ！ うわっ
あれが照明弾かね？
Are those parachute flares?
Hurry, Suzu!
（サン）すずさんも 早よおいで
（騒ぎ声）
Eighth squad, move!
Suzu, what are you doing? Hurry!
（サン）すずさん！
何しとるん 早よ！
すずさん！ すずさん！
Suzu? Suzu?
（すず）ああっ…
ああー！
うわー！
ああーっ
One dropped here?
（径子）すずさん 落ちたかね
Water! We need more water!
（すず）水を！ もっと水
うわーっ
Okay.
（径子）よし いくで よいしょ
（ラジオから流れる声）
Ready...
（ラジオ:男性）０時30分
先に豊後(ぶんご)水道を北進せる敵編隊は
（サン）んっ
よいしょ… 気ぃつけえ
Be careful.
A formation is northbound
via Hiroshima Bay.
広島湾南部を北進中
さらに豊後水道を
北進する１編隊
Another northbound via
Bungo Channel.
および足摺(あしずり)の南西海上に
３目標あり
Three are confirmed
in the seas south of Ashizuri.
情報終わり
こちらはＪＯＦＫ
広島放送局
This is JOFK, Hiroshima
Broadcasting.
こちらはＪＯＦＫ
広島放送局
（半鐘とサイレン）
Hang on, people of Kure!
呉の皆さん
頑張ってください
Persevere, people of Kure!
呉の皆さん
頑張ってください
（男性）罹災(りさい)者の皆さんに―
Anyone suffering hardship...
Please grab rice balls
delivered from Hiroshima!
広島より
握りメシが届いとります
Come get them at Nikou Park.
二河(にこう)公園にて配給
（堂本）罹災証明は
どこでくれるんかいねえ
Where can I file a
damage report?
市役所は まだあるんかのう
Is City Hall still standing?
My house burned down.
うちは はあ丸焼けよね
Avoiding the shelter saved us.
（小林）
壕なんぞ入らんで命拾いじゃ
May I?
（男性）すまんが ええか？
Yes. Go ahead.
はあ どうぞ
（女性）あんた ぬくいうちに食べ
Eat one while it's still warm.
It cooked well as my house
burned down.
床下へしもうとった芋が
ええがに焼けとったけえ
Thank you.
ありゃ いただきます
Keiko...?
お義姉さんも
I've had enough of this heat.
いやあ まいったのう
暑い 暑い…
Is there anyone from Shinonome?
（男性）おーい
東雲町(しののめちょう)の人は おってかのう
The red-light district
burned to the ground.
（男性）朝日町(あさひまち)より南はいけんわ
遊郭も丸焼けよの
I see.
（男性）ほうか
（足音）
（すず）あ…
Suzu!
（周作）すずさん！ おい…
ケガしとんか？
You're hurt.
（すず）訓練は？
（周作）中止じゃ
- Your training?
- Cancelled.
I'm glad that you're alive.
ともかく よかった
あんたが生きとって
As I faded away...
（すず）ぼーっと
かすんでいく中で
Suzu!
すずさん！
I heard myself say, "Find Rin."
（すず）リンさんを捜して…
（周作）すずさん おい！
（すず）
そう うちの声が言うのが聞こえた
I'm glad, anyhow...
（周作）ともかく よかった
I'm glad you're feeling better.
熱が下がって よかった
いやあ よかったのう 不発で
I'm glad it was a dud.
消し止められて よかったねえ
I'm glad it was put out.
I'm glad you're getting better.
（医師）治りが早ようて よかった
（すず）よかった…
I'm glad.
I'm glad... I'm glad...
“よかった よかった”
どこがどう よかったんか
うちには さっぱり分からん
I don't know what
I should be glad about.
My right hand that held
Harumi's hand in June.
６月には
晴美さんとつないだ右手
My right hand that drew
Shusaku's face in May.
５月には 周作さんの寝顔を
描いた右手
My right hand that held
Teru's lip balm in April.
４月には テルさんの紅を
握りしめた右手
２月には お兄ちゃんの脳みそを
拾い上げた右手
My right hand that held
my brother's brain in February.
My right hand that failed to
pattern
去年の11月には お義姉さんの
着物を裁ち間違えた右手
Keiko's kimono
last November.
My right hand that drew
candy for Rin last August.
去年の８月には
リンさんにスイカを描いた右手
My right hand that cooked Lord
Kusunoki's rice...
去年の５月には 楠木公に驚愕(きょうがく)して
箸を落とした右手
My right hand that drew...
去年の３月には…
ふるさとを描き留めた右手…
My right hand that drew
my hometown last February.
My hand that loved to cook...
のりすきが大好きだった右手…
My right hand that drew
many rabbits seven years ago.
７年前の２月には
ウサギをいくつも描いた右手
Your sister is here!
妹さん 見えんさったで
What a disaster, Suzu.
大ごとじゃったねえ
すずちゃん
Sumi, thanks for coming.
すみちゃん
よう来てくれたねえ
The army officer gave me
a lift on the relief truck.
（すみ）
陸軍の将校さんが救援のトラックへ
乗してくれんさってねえ
What is that?
（すず）何？
（すみ）うん
It's not new, but it's
pure cotton.
はい 古着じゃが純綿よ
スフの入っとらんの？
Not rayon?
No, so it's strong.
（すみ）うん 破れんで
うわあ
（足音）
Thank you.
すみません
ほんでこっちは
江波山(えばやま)で採れたビワ
These are loquats from Mt. Eba.
Are you sure?
平気なん？
I need to exercise.
Let me walk you half-way.
起きんと なまってしまうし
途中まで送ってく
I'm meeting him at the
fire station.
消防署の前で待ち合わせなんよ
（すず）ほいじゃあ
川べりのやぐらが目印
It's near the scaffold
by the river,
いや あれも焼けてしもうたかね
or did that burn down, too?
まだ建っとるよ
It's still there. The army
officer showed it to me.
来る時 将校さんに
見してもろうた
若いのに親切な人でねえ
He's young but very kind.
He's been giving me his meal
tickets and other things.
前から食券やらくれてじゃし
うちに呉へお嫁に行った姉がおる
いうんを覚えてくれとってねえ
He remembered that I have
a sister who moved to Kure.
You like him?
好きなんじゃね
Oh please, Suzu.
ありゃあ やじゃわあ
すずちゃん
Ouch.
（すず）あたっ
This is horrible.
（すみ）ひどいねえ
（男性）ああ… よいしょ
It's so sad that Kure
keeps being targeted.
（すみ）呉は何べんも空襲があって
気の毒じゃねえ
ほいで 家のこともできんかったら
おりづらいじゃろう
You must find it hard to be here
not being able to do housework.
Suzu, why don't you
come home to Hiroshima?
ねえ すずちゃん
広島へ帰っておいでえや
（すず）えっ…
The bombings aren't as bad.
（すみ）ひどい空襲もないし―
With our brother gone,
no one will pick on you.
お兄ちゃんも もうおらんけえ
いじめる人もありゃせんで
ほうじゃねえ
I suppose...
I know. I'll come back if your
officer friend is handsome.
すみちゃんの将校さんが
美男子かどうかで決めようかねえ
Why, that's so improper!
ありゃあ 不純なわ
I'm kidding! See you again!
ウソウソ じゃあね
Something is distorted...
（すず）ゆがんどる
It'd be great if you came.
（すみ）ええ考えじゃ思うけどなあ
Come home for the
festival next month.
来月の６日は
江波のお祭りじゃけえ
早よう帰っておいでえね
（すず）ありがとね
すみちゃん
Thanks, Sumi.
I was glad my brother was dead.
（すず）お兄ちゃんが
死んでよかったと思うとる
ゆがんどるのは うちだ
I'm distorted, like a drawing
using my left hand.
左手で描いた絵みたいに
"Record of air raid alerts:
July 3rd to 12th"
（警報）
"July 13th to 16th"
"July 17th "
あっ…
"July 24th to 26th"
（警報）
"July 27th "
07:00 hours, July 28th
（径子）あーあ 今日も来た
Here we go again.
It's going to be a long day.
Pack everything.
（サン）また長(なご)うなりそうなけえ
身の回りのもん持ってのう
（径子）はい あちっ
（サン）すずさん 先へ行き
Suzu, come!
（サギの鳴き声）
（すず）来たらいけん
Don't come here.
You can't be here.
今 ここへは来たらいけん
ああ…
（すず）
そっちじゃ そっちへずーっと逃げ
Yes! Fly away as far as you can,
山を越えたら広島じゃ
over the mountain, to Hiroshima!
（荒い息遣い）
あっ
（周作）死ぬ気か!?
Do you want to die?
I'm sorry. I saw a white heron flying.
（すず）すみません
サギが…
サギが飛びよりましたけえ
（周作）ああ 海辺から
逃げてきたんじゃのう
Oh, it fled from the beach.
Shusaku, I'm going home
to Hiroshima.
周作さん うち―
広島へ帰ります
You intend to stay there?
Is this about your hand?
（周作）戻ってこんつもりか
手のこと気にしとんか？
空襲が怖いんか？
The air raids?
Harumi?
晴美のことか？
Yes, it's all of those things.
（すず）そうです そうです
全部そうです
I can't hear you.
聞こえんわい！
違います！
It's none of that!
Tell me why, then!
じゃあ なんでじゃ
Suzu, I really enjoyed these
18 months we've spent together.
すずさん
わしは 楽しかったで
この１年半
I loved coming home to you,
あんたのおるうちへ帰れて
I loved walking with you
and listening to you talk.
あんたと連ろうて歩くんも
ひらひらしゃべるんも
You don't feel the same?
Am I still a stranger to you?
あんたは違うんか？
ずっと知らんうちのまんまか？
聞こえん
I can't hear you.
聞こえん 聞こえん
いっこも聞こえん
I can't hear a thing,
I'm going home to Hiroshima!
帰る 帰る 広島へ帰る！
Fine.
（周作）おお そうか！
勝手にせえ
Do as you please!
No enemy aircraft over the
Chugoku military district.
（ラジオ:女性）
中国軍管区内上空に敵機なし
Nine days later
07:31 hours,
Hiroshima Prefecture.
広島県地区 ７時31分
Air raid warning lifted.
警戒警報が解除されました
Great timing.
ちょうどええ時間に解除じゃ
We're off.
（小林）
ほいじゃ いってまいります
（小林の妻）ああ
（サン）いってらっしゃい
Take care.
Ouch.
（サン）あいたたた…
そこそこ
That's the spot.
やれ 朝から暑いこと
What a hot morning.
We're going to miss you, Suzu.
寂しいねえ
すずさんが おらんくなるんは
So what time is your
doctor's appointment?
で 何時からね？
（すず）へ？
（径子）病院
About 10 o'clock.
はあ 10時頃です
（径子）ハア… その格好はいけん
You need to change.
Here.
うん
Excuse me...
すみません あの…
ああ… こりゃ洗濯じゃなかったね
I guess we won't need
to wash this.
Isn't your hometown's
festival today?
今日なんね
あんたの里のお祭り
Yes. I was going to
go home last weekend,
ええ
週末に帰るつもりが
病院の予約が今日しか取れんで
but I couldn't get
an appointment until today.
Don't look!
見んでええ
すみません
I'm sorry.
You'll never make it today.
Doctors are busy too, you know.
（径子）どうせ間に合いやせんよ
お医者さんじゃって忙しいのに
You'll need a referral as well.
広島の病院へ紹介状も
書いてもらわにゃならんのじゃろう
Train tickets are usually sold
out anyway.
第一 汽車の切符が取れんもん
うん
Here, I've fixed your
sister's kimono.
妹さんの純綿
もんぺに直しといたで
I added rubber straps so you can
wear it easily.
ゴムひも通したけえ
１人で着られよう
ゴムが寄せ集めで申し訳ないが
They're all I
could scrap together.
あ… ありがとうございます
Thank you very much...
I'm sorry I blamed you
for Harumi's death.
悪かった 晴美が死んだんを
あんたのせいにして
いいえ
It's okay.
"Kuromura Clockwork"
（径子）私は好いた人に
早よ死なれた
The man I loved died young.
My shop was destroyed.
店も疎開で壊された
I can't see my children anymore.
子供とも会えんくなった
ほいでも
自分で選んだ道の果てじゃけえ
But my own choices led me here.
その点 あんたは―
You had no choice, though.
You were brought here.
周りの言いなりに
知らん家に嫁に来て
You did what you were told.
言いなりに働かされて
What a boring life this
must've been.
さぞや つまらん人生じゃろ思うわ
You're welcome to stay here
or go anywhere you choose.
すずさんの居場所は
ここでもええし どこでもええ
Stop worrying and
choose for yourself.
くだらん気兼ねはなしに
自分で決め
（すず･径子）えっ？
Keiko. Did you see that flash?
（小林の妻）径子ちゃん
今 何か光ったかね
I did!
光った
雷じゃろうか ええ天気のに
Could it be lightning
in this weather?
あの… やっぱり これ―
I... changed my mind...
Can you wash this, please?
洗(あろ)うてもらえますか
ほいで やっぱり―
And please, would you
let me stay?
ここへおらしてもらえますか
ああ 分かった
分かったけえ離れえ 暑苦しい
Yes, now let me go. It's
too hot for that!
何じゃ？ 今のは
What was that?
The JOFK isn't coming in.
（径子）
いけん ＪＯＦＫが何も聞こえん
The other stations?
よそは？
Hey!
（円太郎）おーい
Come over here and look.
こっち来て見てみい
What is that cloud?
（小林の妻）何じゃ？ あの雲は
（径子）えっ？ ああ…
Cloud?
（すず）雲？
Look at that big cloud.
It's an anvil cloud.
（すず）大きな雲じゃろう
カナトコ雲よ
This is Okayama Broadcasting.
Hiroshima, do you read me?
（ラジオ:男性）こちら岡山放送局
広島放送局？ 広島放送局？
こちら岡山放送局
I found a flyer from all the way
from Hiroshima on the street.
（女性）
いや 何か落ちとる思うたら
広島の回覧板じゃったわ
（女性たち）ああ…
手の空いとる人
後で隣保館 寄ってくださいや
Anyone available, please come to
the settlement house.
（小林の妻）ほう 知多さんは
看護婦じゃったんかね
Chita, aren't you a nurse?
Yes, but I've never
made sandals.
（知多）はあ 草履なんて
作ったことないですがね
No one around here has.
（径子）この辺の人は
皆 そうじゃ
Is this okay?
こいでええんかね
ああ 片手じゃ
うもうできんで歯ぐいいわ
It's frustrating with one hand.
そりゃ 嫌みかね
Now you're just gloating...
What are these sandals for?
（すず）ほいで この草履
どうするんですか？
They're for Hiroshima.
（知多）広島へね
先月の空襲みとうに
道路が溶けとったら―
That flash melted the roads so
shoes are no good.
靴もゲタもいけんけえ
うちも行けますか？
Can I come too?
The wounded must stay.
（知多）ケガ人は行けん
うちは息子が広島へ
兵隊に取られとるし
My son is a soldier
in Hiroshima.
You can join us tomorrow.
（知多）ほいじゃあ
明日のトラック乗るかね？
呉の空襲じゃ
広島がようけ助けてくれたけえ
Hiroshima helped us before,
now it's our turn to help them.
お返しせんと…
あっ
My hair won't get in the way
now. Take me, please.
これで結う手間も省ける
迷惑かけんようしますけえ
I said no!
いけん
Silly girl. I'll trim your hair
when we get home.
また アホやって
早よ帰って 切りそろえよう
My husband is going to
Hiroshima soon.
（小林の妻）うちの人も
近いうち 広島行くいうし まあ
I hear it was a new
type of bomb.
広島へは
新型爆弾が落とされたらしい
Oh no.
ありゃりゃ
Suzu, your family...
（サン）
すずさんがたは大丈夫…
お母ちゃん
Mum!
The navy base sent a
relief party.
鎮守府からも救援が出とるし
まあ…
んっ…
You came from Hiroshima, too?
（すず）
あんたも広島から来たんね
He died sitting here.
（知多）
座ったまんま亡くなりんさってかね
He walked all the way
from Hiroshima.
（刈谷）
広島から ここまで歩いてきて
（堂本）はあ…
どこの誰かも分かりゃせん
But we couldn't tell
who he was...
顔も服もベロベロで
Because his face and
clothes had melted...
Let's not tell Mrs. Houjo.
（刈谷）
北條の嫁さんには黙っとこうで
（堂本）あの子の顔 よう見れんよ
気の毒で
I can't face her. I feel so bad.
（知多）ハッ…
I picked eucalyptus leaves
to keep mosquitoes away.
（すず）ユーカリの葉
つんできましたけえ
蚊やりに使(つこ)うてつかあさい
Thank you. Stay strong, okay?
ありがとうね
気をしっかり持つんよ
I will. Their names are, Juro,
Kiseno and Sumi Urano.
はい ほいで…
江波の浦野十郎 キセノ すみ
Understood.
（知多）うん
（すず）
草津の森田イト マリナ 千鶴子
And also Ito, Marina and Chizuko
Morita.
うちも強うなりたいよ
優しゅう しぶとうなりたいよ
I want to stay strong.
Kind but strong.
Like the people of Kure.
この町の人らみたいに
Ah, this rubbish again...
ああ うるさいね
We'll never surrender
to violence.
そんとな暴力に屈するもんかね
August 9th
ここへ おらしてください
ずっと
Please let me stay.
Forever.
You had me worried. You dummy.
心配かけおって
このアホが！
Dummy, dummy...
アホ アホ アホ ア…
I'm sorry.
（すず）すみません
（周作）ああ
I'm sorry. I'm so sorry.
ほんまに すみません
（すず）すみません
（周作）ああ
I missed all of them.
（周作）１個も当たりゃせん
I'd never hear the end of it
if the Navy knew...
こりゃまた
海兵団で いびられるのう
すずさん 米軍の伝単は
拾うたら届けんと
Suzu, this is US propaganda.
It should be handed to
the authorities.
また憲兵さんに叱られるで
They'll burn it anyway.
届けても燃やしんさるだけです
So I gather them
to use them as toilet paper.
こうして もんで
落とし紙にするほうが―
無駄がのうてええ
ごもっとも
I see, then we can't let people
use our toilet for a while.
じゃが当分 便所は人に貸せんのう
Our battle is to survive
with whatever we have.
何でも使うて暮らし続けるのが
うちらの戦いですけえ
I suppose.
（周作）はーん
Please, come in.
あっ 上がってください
August 15th
（刈谷･堂本）どうも
Hello.
（ラジオ:天皇）
戦陣に死し職域に殉し―
We are keenly aware of the
innermost feelings of all of you,
非命に倒れたる者 および
その遺族に思いを致せば―
Our subjects. However, it is
according to the dictates of
五内(ごだい)ために裂く
time and fate that
かつ戦傷を負い
災禍をこうむり―
We have resolved to pave the
way for a grand peace
家業を失いたる者の厚生に…
for all the generations to come
by enduring the unendurable and
耐え難きを耐え
忍び難きを忍び
suffering what is insufferable.
もって万世のために…
（ラジオ:男性）
謹みて天皇陛下の玉音放送を…
Thus ends the His Majesty the
Emperor's honorable broadcast.
（径子）
ハア… 終わった 終わった
Oh well. It's finally over.
で こりゃあ…
So, this means...
We lost the war?
負けたということかね？
Why?
なんで？
広島と長崎に
新型爆弾 落とされたし
They dropped those new bombs
on Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
The Soviets have declared war.
We couldn't possibly win.
ソビエトも参戦したし
まあ かなわんわ
（すず）
そんなん覚悟の上じゃないんかね
They knew what we were getting
into, didn't they?
最後の１人まで
戦うんじゃなかったんかね
They said we would
fight to the end!
今ここへ まだ５人おるのに
There's five of us still here!
I still have my left arm
and both legs.
まだ左手も両足も残っとるのに
ううー！ ああ！ うう！
（径子の泣き声）
Harumi.
（径子）晴美…
ウウ… 晴美…
Harumi...
（すず）飛び去っていく
うちらのこれまでが
Everything we've
done slips away.
それでいいと思ってきたものが
Everything we've come
to terms with.
だから我慢しようと思ってきた
その理由が
The reasons why we've
endured it all.
ああ… 海の向こうから来た
お米 大豆
Rice and soybeans grown overseas,
that's what my body is made of.
そんなもんで できとるんじゃなあ
うちは
じゃけえ 暴力にも
屈せんとならんのかね
So we surrender to violence?
（泣き声）
ああ… 何も考えん
ぼーっとしたうちのまま―
If only I could stay distracted
and oblivious until I die.
死にたかったなあ
（泣き声）
いよいよなったら―
I stocked this for
our last meal.
最後に みんなで思うて
ためといたんじゃけど
So let's enjoy white
rice tonight.
今日は 何も混ぜんで炊こうや
But not all of it.
全部はいけんよ
There's still a tomorrow
and the day after that.
まだまだ明日も あさっても
あるんじゃけえ
（すず）あっ
（径子）ああ…
August 15th and 16th...
（すず）８月15日も 16日も
and 17th.
17日も
９月も
September.
10月も
October, November and next year.
11月も来年も
再来年も10年後も
A year later, 10 years later.
Forever and ever.
ずっと ずっと
（２人）うわあ
Look, it's a glorious white!
（円太郎）
ああ 輝くように真っ白じゃのう
We only have rice.
（すず）おかずが何にものうて
Not to worry. Where's Shusaku?
何の 周作は？
Not home, yet.
まだ
ここに至って
なお秩序を守るんが法務の仕事か
I suppose it's the
legal office's job
to keep order in
times like this.
先にいただこうや
Let's start eating.
No more bombs, so no more
floating fish.
もう爆弾落ちんから
魚も浮かんねえ
（サン）あん時ゃねえ
I remember that time, yes.
（晴美の笑い声）
（すず）ハッ…
（円太郎）何しとんのじゃ
What are we doing? I can't see
my beautiful white rice.
せっかくの白いメシが見えん
October 6th
（周作）いよいよ上陸してきよる
They'll be landing soon.
I'll be stationed in Ootake.
わしらは大竹(おおたけ)へ移る
As long as our navy stands, it's
our obligation to keep order.
海軍を解体しきるまでは
何があっても―
秩序を守り通すのが
法務の仕事じゃ
In times like this...
（すず）ああ…
こげな時 両手があれば―
I wish I had both hands, so I
could hold his to comfort him.
この人の不安な手に
そっと片手を重ねられるのに
It's so quiet.
（すず）静かですね
Everything's ready.
（周作）皆 準備がええ
Thank you. Here is fine.
すまんかった ここでええ
（すず）えっ
Go back home quickly.
はあ 早ようちへ帰れ
じゃあの
Goodbye.
わしは絶対 帰ってくるけえ
すずさんとこへのう
I'll be back! I'll
come home to you!
はい
Yes!
"Rice rations postponed"
お塩や おしょうゆは
もう ずっとない
We haven't had salt or
soy sauce for quite a while.
November 1945
Keiko!
あっ お義姉さん
Hi Suzu, do you know
what this queue is for?
ああ すずさん
こりゃ 何の行列かねえ
さあ 何でもええですよ
何でも足らんのですけえ
No idea, but I'll take
anything gladly.
We're short on everything.
Well, that's true.
まあ 確かに
しかし変わったねえ この街も
The city has changed.
（子供）ギブ ミー
I wonder if Hisao begs for chocolate too.
（径子）久夫も今頃
あがいなまね しとんじゃろうか
Would Harumi have done the same?
晴美もしたんじゃろうか
占領軍の残飯雑炊でした
はあ…
It's leftovers of the
occupation army.
（径子）紙クズが…
Paper waste?
（すず）うっ
（径子）うっ
（２人）うっ うっ うっ…
So... delicious!
うまー
こっちは全然 味がない
This one's flavorless.
I gave the Americans directions
and they gave me chocolate.
（すず）ほいで うちは
アメリカさんに道を教えてあげたら
チョコレートもろうたです
With that hair style,
they thought you were a child.
（刈谷）その髪形じゃし
子供と間違われたんじゃわ
（すず）ハハハ…
（すず）ええんですか？
あんとに洋服を交換して
You exchanged so many clothes.
It's all right.
（刈谷）ええんよ
Didn't you hear?
知らんかね
The dead soldier found next to
the settlement house was my son.
隣保館で行き倒れとった兵隊が
うちの息子じゃったらしい
I couldn't recognize my own son.
自分の息子と
気づかんかったんよ うちは
You lost Harumi in
front of your eyes.
あんたも目の前で晴美さんを…
ええ 残念です
Yes. It was awful.
Suzu.
（哲）すず
すず
Smile, when you think of me.
わしを思い出すなら
笑うてくれ
I want you to stay
ordinary and sane.
この世界で普通で
まともでおってくれ
Suzu.
すず
（すず）晴美さん
Harumi. I can see the ship now.
何の船がおりんさるか
見えたよ 晴美さん
It's the Aoba.
おったのは青葉よ
哲さん
Tetsu, I just saw it in
your smile...
今 あんたの笑顔の端に―
The sea with white rabbits,
the sky with white herons...
ウサギの跳ねる海が
サギの渡る空が宿っとった
（晴美の笑い声）
Harumi always laughed, so I'll
laugh whenever I think of her.
（すず）晴美さんは
よう笑うてじゃし―
晴美さんのことは
笑うて思い出してあげよう思います
From now on, this body will
be here to smile.
この先ずっと
うちは笑顔の入れ物なんです
That's right. It'd be a waste
to cry all the time.
ほうよ 泣いてばっかりじゃ
もったいない
It's a waste of salt.
（２人）塩分がねえ
（一同）くう～
Thank heavens for
the salty seas!
海の塩水様々じゃねえ
Grandma! Auntie! Chizuko!
おばあちゃん おばちゃん
千鶴子ちゃん
January 1946
（マリナ）ありゃあ
（千鶴子）すずちゃん
Suzu!
Sumi?
すみちゃん
Suzu! You cut your hair.
（すみ）あっ！ すずちゃん
髪の毛 切ったんじゃねえ
Don't get up. Are you ill?
（すず）ええ ええ 起きんで
具合悪いん？
ちいと めまいがするだけ
I'm a little dizzy.
（すず）えっ…
What a shame big sister.
ああ 無念じゃ 姉上
I can't help with work outside
on this cold bitter day.
この寒空の下
のりの仕事が手伝えんとは
I suppose you must rest
easy for now.
それは おとなしゅう
寝とらんといけんねえ
（２人）フフフ…
ああ 手がありゃ―
If only I had my hand,
お兄ちゃんの南洋冒険記でも
描いてあげられるのにねえ
I'd draw "Yoichi's Adventures
in the South Seas."
それ どんな？
ねえ どんな話？
What would the story be about?
Yoichi's troop transport
gets shipwrecked.
お兄ちゃん 輸送船が難破して
南の島にヤシの葉で家作って
So he builds a house
with palm leaves on an island.
He grows a beard and
marries a crocodile.
ヒゲぼうぼうになって
ワニをお嫁さんにして
A crocodile for a bride.
（すみ）ワニがお嫁さんかあ
江波へ帰っとらんかね お兄ちゃん
I wish Yoichi could
come back to Eba.
And Mom, too.
お母ちゃんも
What?
えっ？
On the morning of the festival,
Mom went shopping in the city.
あの朝 お祭りの支度で
お母ちゃん 街へお使い行ってね
Dad and I looked everywhere,
but couldn't find her.
お父ちゃんと うちとで
捜し回ったけど―
見つからんかったんよ
お父ちゃん 10月に倒れて
すぐ死んでしもうた
Dad fell ill in October
and died soon after.
He was cremated along with
others at school.
学校でまとめて焼いてもろうた
I should have told you sooner.
知らせる暇のうて ごめんね
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry I couldn't
come sooner.
早よ来れんで ごめんね
I'm glad you didn't.
（すみ）早よ来んでよかったよ
Suzu, look at me.
すずちゃん うち こんなよ
Will I get better?
うち 治るかねえ
（すず）治るよ
治らんと おかしいよ
Yes, of course you will!
Sachiko!
（女性）あっ！ サチコさん！
Sorry.
（すず）いえ
（女性）ああ…
Kiyoko! Aren't you Kiyoko?
（男性）キヨコさん
キヨコさんじゃろ？
（すず）この街では
皆 誰かをなくし 捜している
Everyone lost someone,
and they're still looking.
I think I saw Rin a few times,
too.
うちも リンさんを２～３度
見かけたような気がした
ハア…
（周作）すずさん
Suzu.
（すず）あっ ようご無事で
You're back.
海軍も11月いっぱいでのうなった
お役御免じゃ
The Navy was disbanded
at the end of November.
I've been let go.
Suzu, this is the bridge
where I first met you.
すずさん
わしとすずさんが初めて会うたんは
この橋の上じゃった
We can't go back in time.
もう あの頃には戻らん
We'll keep changing,
this city and us.
この街も わしらも
変わり続けていくんじゃろうが―
But I will always
tell you apart.
わしは すずさんが
いつでも分かる
I'll find this beauty
mark right away.
ここへ ほくろがあるけえ
すぐ分かるで
周作さん ありがとう
Thank you, for finding me
in this Corner of the World.
この世界の片隅に
うちを見つけてくれて
Please never leave, and
always be by my side.
ほんで もう離れんで
ずっとそばにおってください
Huh?
（２人）うん？ えっ？
（爆発音）
（女性）ハア ハア ハア…
（子供）うっ ううっ うう…
（すず）あっ
（周作）ええ ええ
- Oh...
- Let it be.
I'm glad I found a job
in Hiroshima.
とにかく広島で
仕事が見つかったけえ よかった
（すず）ええ
Me, too.
The commute will be difficult.
でも 遠うて大変ですね
うちは… えっ…
I... what?
Thank you. But you can have it.
ありがとう
ええよ 食べんさい
いっそ うちを出て
こっちで所帯持つか
We could leave Kure
and start over here.
お義母さんやら
すみさんのこともあるし
For your family's sake.
No, I can commute.
いえいえ
それは うちがこっちへ通います
I'm worried about Hiroshima
広島のことも心配じゃけど
呉はうちが選んだ場所ですけえ
but Kure is the town I
chose to live in.
Oh?
ありゃ…
It's okay.
うん
Next stop, Kure.
（駅員）呉～ 呉～
Kure?
（子供）呉？
That's right. This is Kure.
そうよ ここが呉
九つの嶺(みね)に守られとるんで
ほいで九嶺(くれ)いうんで
"Kure" means we are
protected by nine mountains.
On your right is Mt. Yasumi,
to the left is Mt. Hachimaki.
右のんは休山(やすみやま) 左のんは鉢巻山(はちまきやま)
And in the center is Mt.
Haigamine.
ほいで 真ん中のんが灰ヶ峰
あのすそが わしらのうちじゃ
That's where our home is.
This child...
（サン）この子…
（すず）ありゃ
She's covered in lice!
（円太郎）ものすごいシラミじゃ
Hurry, we have to boil all
of our clothes!
大鍋に湯沸かし
着とるもんも みんな煮るで
We should start with a bath.
とりあえず風呂かのう
She should go in last.
この子は最後のほうが
ええんじゃないですか？
（円太郎）
まあ とにかく風呂に へえ
I'll start the fire.
I wonder if Harumi's clothes
would be too small.
去年の晴美の服じゃ
こまいかねえ
♪～
～♪